I have seen things, you know, that make
me want to close my eyes for sure.
You know, you want to talk about the
dark side and that's okay.
I hope no one would do this, but I know
people do. That's my opening gambit for
I want to take it over. After this
conversation I'm a little more
cynical.
This is Ethan Evans, former Amazon VP,
back for a second time because I knew he
had a lot to share about corporate
politics. We're going to put these
people under you for 6 months, check the
box, and give them back to the person we
took them from.
>> [music]
>> It's almost like this hidden chess going
on.
>> Absolutely. He shared what to do if you
have a bad manager. You could consider
this as mutiny [music] if you went to
them and you said, "Hey, my manager is
bad." So, mutiny. Let's talk about
mutiny. And he said he'd be transparent,
so I really put him to the test. What
are the attacker tactics?
Wow, Ryan. When you said we would just
go deep on transparency, you were not
kidding. So, the best attack What is the
>> leverage that an engineer has as they're
getting fired that a company would want
to pay for? And here I'll give you your
last piece of your leverage. I imagine
this would be useful even outside of
your career. Now, there's some people
watching this, engineers, who are like,
"I hate you. I hate the politics." Do
yourself a favor and get good at this.
Here's the full episode.
Last time we talked, I think one reason
that people really loved the
conversation was because of your unusual
level of transparency. I've never met
anyone who was in such a high level in
tech, like in VP at Amazon, that was
willing to say everything directly that
could help both engineers and also
managers know what's going on behind the
scenes at those highest levels.
And I know that we didn't get to cover
everything. So, today I'm hoping that we
can go over everything in terms of
reorgs and all of the other
behind-the-scenes things that happened
in the management of tech. So, I'm
hoping you can continue to be
transparent, maybe even more transparent
this time.
Absolutely. You know, I'm comfortable
with the fact that
I'm not a perfect person and sometimes
some of the stuff I did, I wish I had
done differently. So, I can share what I
did and what I saw others do
because I'm comfortable with that and
frankly I'm retired, so I'm immune.
There's no boss over me who's going to
be like, "You said what? You told Ryan
what?"
I'm free from that.
The first topic I want to go over is
empire building.
Uh empire building, I think, is a bad
thing. And it, as defined, it means
focusing more on getting raw number of
people than on what you're doing or the
impact you're having.
So, why does it exist?
Empire building exists because it's
rewarded.
And it's rewarded
because
counting people is the easiest thing to
do.
And so, when a leader or set of leaders
are deciding who's ready to promote,
how much impact you had is subjective.
One person thinks the project was hard,
another thinks, "Oh, that was pretty
easy."
But no one can debate, "Well, Ethan has
42 people
and Ryan has 17. Ethan is the bigger
leader." is the conclusion they're
making.
And that
encourages empire building because it's
what's visibly measurable.
And so, what I found is
that drives leaders to want more people
because that's going to be their tool.
And some companies
absolutely have
written thresholds of to be eligible for
this promotion, you have to have this
many people. So, of course,
if you give high performers a goal,
they're going to figure out a way to hit
that goal. And if that requires claiming
they need people or seeking to take over
other groups, they're ambitious.
They're going to find a way to
rationalize that to them to themselves,
"I need those people." I saw that
there's this this desire to change the
incentive structure, at least at the
company that I was at, um where managers
could be promoted not necessarily just
with the directly proportional to how
many recursive reports you have. Is that
possible to do?
Of course it is possible. It takes more
effort.
Uh because impact is harder to assess,
right? The impact an engineering manager
has is somewhat fuzzy. What's most
important? Is it operational
performance? Is it new features shipped?
Is it whether or not those new features
resonate in the market and make money?
And you end up with difficulties like
maybe my product directly generates
money. Whatever I'm doing gets directly
sold and customers pay for it. And what
you're doing is infrastructure.
Well, now, how do we compare that? Like,
you're keeping the systems up, but I'm
actually the one bringing in all the
money. Who has more impact?
Again, that's where people get sucked
into, "Why I have 42 people and you have
17? I must be a bigger manager." That's
that's how that happens. It is, of
course, possible to make value
judgments, but then they're also harder
to defend. I have to look at you and
say,
"Ryan, we love the work you've done and
you're on the right path, but Ethan was
more impactful."
And that just makes you mad, probably,
unless you happen to agree like, "Oh,
yeah, that guy's a star."
It's it's all these things make
assessing impact
difficult and dangerous and that's why
it doesn't get done as much as it
should.
You mentioned the written thresholds for
promotion and since you were a VP at
Amazon, I know it's been some time, but
off the top of your head, do you
remember the rough
written thresholds for how many reports
you would need to be considered for
senior management, director, and VP? So,
interestingly, those thresholds did not
exist while I was there.
And they existed in whisper numbers, but
they were not written down.
They came about after I left and people
I was coaching still at Amazon or
talking to told me very clearly that the
number that got established to become a
director
in some orgs was people and in some was
90.
So, I became a director in the early
days of the company with 22 people
because it was different times and the
company was smaller. And that crept up
and up until when I was at the end of my
career,
we did have like a sense that the
company wanted us to look for people
with about 75 or 80 people.
But it got written down as 90, at least
in some organizations. And the thing
that's funny about that
is one of the Amazon leadership
principles says, "There's no bonus for
additional head count."
But now that it's written down that I
can't get to this very well-paying level
without 90 people,
there damn sure is a bonus. Right?
There's like a several hundred thousand
dollar a year bonus, quite literally,
for accumulating 90 people.
And
I've talked to leaders
who their boss trying to get them across
the threshold was like, "We're going to
put these people under you for 6 months,
check the box, and give them back to the
person we took them from." Because
that's the game they have to play if
they want to, you know, reward a person
in their team. And of course, that's
insanity where
we're moving people around and changing
their lives just to hit a number.
But if you did that, let's say I'm I'm a
VP and I have a very loud director or
very loud senior manager who wants to
become a director. And so, I got, "Okay,
to retain them, I'm going to give them
some reports from over here and now
they're going to be eligible for
director." After they get promoted,
though,
they need to sustain those reports to
sustain that position, right? Like, you
couldn't just move them back and
>> you can. Again, it depends on the
company, but you can play all sorts of
shell games
where
um
for example, at Amazon, if you drop
below the number of reports, there's
like a grace period, 6 months, 9 months,
where if you can tell a story about how
they're going to get back to that level
or how future growth, it's okay if
they're below it temporarily. The other
thing is, no company no company I know
of really systematically down-levels
people. What they would do is they'd
say, "Okay, well, Ryan, you're a
director. Your team is no longer
director scope. You're going to have to
find a director level role." And so,
then it's up to me if I can do that in
my org or I move you, but I still
achieved the goal for you.
And you absolutely see, I have seen, not
just in Amazon, but other places,
when head count is the main issue, I've
seen things moved around and I certainly
when people normally come to me, it's
with the complaint,
"My boss actually told me that he's
putting me under my peer so that my
peer's team will look better.
So, the reason I'm being reorged under
this other person is not for any
business reason,
but because they don't have the scope to
get the promotion. And so, I need to go
be their scope."
Mhm. That's what I'm being told. When I
was an engineer and reorgs were
happening, I think you don't know all
the behind-the-scenes of how orgs are
managed. And so, you're told there's a
certain reason for the reorg. However,
and which may be true, but there may be
a secondary and ulterior motive of this
person also needs to get promoted. Do
you ever have a experience like that
where you saw a reorg happening in
another org? You didn't know the exact
person who needs to get promoted or
what, but you could just tell based on
how it happened and
uh what happened that oh, there's
something else going on behind the
scenes.
Yeah, and I would say there's always
something else going on. Meaning, all
managers know all leaders know that too
many reorgs cost you people. And so you
don't want to do them too often.
What that means though is like you wait
as long as you can and then when you
need to do one, you're asking yourself
how do we get everything we want?
How do we How do we if there's someone
we don't like, how do we give them less
so they'll move on? If there's someone
that we really think is high
performance, how do we set them up for
success? How do we retain key people?
And yes, hopefully the start of the
reorg is how do we make the business
better?
But as soon as we figure out what we
think we need to do for the business,
then we're trying to figure out how much
else, you know, this ship is leaving the
dock. How much else can we throw on the
deck as it's pulling away that's going
to help us? I'm just trying to figure
out the exact mechanics. Like maybe a
past reorg that you've done where
you tried to cram a bunch of different
ulterior things into it. And how does
that actually play out?
Well,
um
a couple things happen there. First,
there are usually multiple people
involved and so
sometimes
you have to either get them on board
with your second motive. You you know,
you have to tell them like yeah, I want
to help this person get promoted as a
part of this reorg or I want to set them
up. Are you supportive of that?
Sometimes you have to tell a story like
no, I'm not doing that. It's really this
reason. And so there is some cleverness
to justifying.
Because
even for a senior leader, usually a
reorg is a big enough change that
somebody will be auditing it and you've
got to be able to explain it to them. So
you're coming up with your narrative.
You're a storyteller and you're coming
up with your narrative about why this is
the best possible reorg that rewards the
deserving people and accomplishes the
business goals and if anybody is
suffering, you've made sure that that's
people that aren't the highest
performers. So if anybody does leave,
it's okay.
And when I think about specific reorgs
I've done,
they're very much about retention. If
you're making a change, you're very much
thinking
people don't like change.
Who is it I absolutely need to keep and
who is it if they leave, I'll either be
okay or even maybe happy.
Um
and
I can't immediately think of a place
where I
personally put someone in a role where
I'm like am I putting them there,
they'll quit.
But I can absolutely think of the
reverse where people I really wanted to
keep, maybe who I felt I was at risk of
losing, I was using the reorg to give
them something juicier.
So then how does it usually get started?
I mean a reorg. Let's say yeah, what's
the the triggering condition?
Well, usually the the triggering
condition is
a change in the business. So
um something about the business has
changed and the organization is not set
up to address it. So it needs to take on
a new market or you've acquired a
company and you need to blend them in or
you want to start a new project. That's
the first reason for a reorg is change
in the business.
The second reason for a reorg is
somebody else quit or got moved.
So often reorgs come due to cascades and
many times, for example, several times
in my career,
my boss either left or was moved to
another job. And so I had to go
somewhere else. I could go up if they
thought I was ready, I could go under
somebody different
or they could choose to backfill. Uh you
know, just leave that position open. But
at least in my personal experience at
Amazon,
I never really saw the backfill happen.
I always was moved under another leader.
And several times I'm pretty sure I was
put under them to stretch them.
Uh when I ran
the Prime Video team,
my leader left
and I was reorged from being under an
engineering VP to being placed under a
business leader. And that business
leader, who turned out to be one of my
best managers ever, some of his first
words to me were
I don't really want your team.
Uh I don't want to run engineering. I
don't know anything about it. And of
course as an engineer, I'm like uh-oh.
Um but he was a good leader and he said
we will figure it out. And we worked
together and actually had a great run.
But I had that happen a couple times
where I was put under people and it was
they had never led engineering and it's
like well, let's give him Ethan's team
and let him figure out engineering.
Which could be really demoralizing,
right? Like okay, here's the person
who's not technical and I'm their guinea
pig.
In conducting a reorg, you mentioned
that
you're the storyteller and you're
building a narrative. And you said in
some cases you'd be direct and you'd say
we're trying to retain this person so
we're going to move things around.
And in other cases you said
you you would tell a story that this is
solving a problem for the business and
that that other part would be hidden.
It's really interesting to me cuz
there's
it's almost like this hidden chess going
on Absolutely. You're aware of there's
multiple things and you're aware of the
messenger of
this is what this person
wants to hear and here are the things
that I'm trying to achieve. What pieces
of what I'm trying to do can I sell to
them
to make the reorg happen and also you'll
get maybe other things as a result.
And I think that turns off a lot of
people, especially engineers. They go I
don't I don't want to be
managing all these. I just want to say
it as it is. Is that just a inevitable
thing that you have to deal with if
you're in management? Well, inevitable,
you can certainly work around it.
Meaning you can just do a reorg purely
based on business goals and not let any
concern for people enter.
But probably
that's going to cost you people.
Because
some people are more ambitious than
others or just more demanding.
And there is some truth to the old
saying the squeaky wheel gets the
grease.
This is another harsh truth people don't
like. Sometimes, let's say two people
perform roughly equally, but one of them
has made really clear that they're
thinking about leaving.
Well, a lot of managers will ask
themselves,
you know, Ryan's this great guy always
sticks with us.
He'll wait another 6 months and I can
use those 6 months to save this other
guy who's also valuable.
And and
by being quiet and dutiful, sometimes I
can make the decision
it's not that I mean
to screw you. It's more
I'm focused on saving this other person
and I know you'll put up with it.
And so you can end up behind just
because you're such a nice guy.
And uh I often tell people when I'm
coaching them, I will often tell my
clients,
you are a very nice person.
And when I tell them that, what they
don't know is I'm then going to say and
that is not a compliment. In this
context, right? That like this is
Again, I don't think you need to be a
jerk,
but jerks
up to a point,
pushy people get more. Now they can push
too far
and then they get less because they've
antagonized.
But if you never ask for anything,
you'll never get anything.
And so in a reorg,
you ask about what's inevitable. Well,
what's inevitable is I have some people
who have been more vocal about what they
want in their career than others.
Perhaps I'm
arranging the reorg just because
I know what some people want and I don't
know what others want and so I assume
they'll be fine.
That's the most benign version. It may
be
even more that for some people I know
they're very pushy and demanding and for
some people I know they're not and so
I'm serving the pushy people cuz then I
get to keep my whole team. So it seems
like almost always it's better to be
pushy and forthcoming with what you want
in your career,
but there is an upper bound though where
you go too far. And so
to to empire building for instance, a
concrete example. I mean, have you ever
had someone who was
a manager underneath you and clearly
asking for reports and you could you
could see immediately that you don't
need these reports. You're pushing
because this is going to lead to your
eventual promotion.
And how do you handle that as a manager
or as a senior leader when you can see
someone's being too pushy and it's
obviously not good for the business and
not defendable?
Yeah, so
I think of manager, if I'm in the
leadership seat, first I better
have a good trusting relationship with
that person if possible where we can
have a heart to heart and I can get in a
room where they don't feel anybody's
listening or watching and say look,
let's talk for a minute why you really
want these people.
Okay, let's both be honest that you're
empire building and I get that. You're
trying to get to a goal.
But this is a bridge too far. Let's talk
about how I'm going to get you there or
how we're going to get you there
by some defendable path or some other
path. And so as opposed to tell them
just no you can't have this, which would
be very frustrating and they'll probably
argue, I try to bend the conversation to
let's problem solve together. What's
another way to do this?
And
um
I won't say I'm always successful. Some
people want what they want right now and
they can't see or they have zero
patience to wait.
And at that point again, that's that
fine line.
Uh if I can, I'll share a related
example that I know people resonate with
where one time I wanted to tell my
manager that I really expected to be
promoted.
But I wanted to do it in a diplomatic
way that couldn't get me in trouble and
and wouldn't irritate him. Not just
couldn't get me in deep trouble but like
would bring out his support even though
I was threatening a little.
And so what I did is with this manager
I wanted to be a director at Amazon. I
was a senior manager. It's when I had
the 22 people I referred to earlier.
I went to him and his name was Neil.
And I said, "Neil
I need to understand how important my
career is to Amazon.
Because my career is very important to
me.
And see that's a statement no one can
argue with. No one can argue and say,
"Well, your career shouldn't be
important to you or it's illogical."
So I said, "My career is very important
to me. I need to understand how
important it is to Amazon.
Because
if it's not as important to Amazon
as it is to me
I need to think about that."
And
you know, I need to think about that
isn't a direct threat, but you laughed.
Everyone understands that I'm
kind of serving notice.
But I'm not doing it in a way that is
easily easy for him to push back on. See
if I say, "Well, if it's not as
important to you." Making it personal
with him. "It's not important to you as
it is to me
then I might quit."
That's a threat and all managers are
going to be like, "Hey, you can't extort
me."
Right? That isn't how it works.
So I came up with these words
that
clearly conveyed the message but in a
way
you can't argue with it's important to
me. You can't argue really that if if
it's not as important to Amazon, I
didn't personalize it. You know, that
that I have to think about that.
That you know, so I was able to put it
on the table.
And you know, um he promoted me, right?
He pushed the promotion through.
And
I think there's always a way to say
things
in that middle ground that makes clear
what you want and makes clear that
you're willing to consider your other
options but without being a threatening
jerk about it.
That wording is um
it's it's kind of in for I mean cuz when
you say the wording, I
feel I mean if I was in I feel the
effects of extortion a bit. Right? But I
couldn't I could not label it extortion.
If I went to someone else and I I went
to my management and said, "Hey, Ethan
told me this."
They would they would have probably also
immediately get, "Oh, there's a there's
a threat here." But I don't think anyone
in any room would say "This guy's being
mean with it or or we need to get rid of
him." They'd say, "That's uh
well done way to present yourself."
Right. That's bold. He's clear on what
he wants and that's, you know, one of
the advantages do find a place where you
fit.
Meaning Amazon was a relatively sharp
elbowed pushy place. It has that
reputation today. It was true long ago.
You have to tune your message
to to the workplace that you're in. That
message would be offensive in some
workplaces.
And it was totally not offensive at
Amazon because there were people sort of
pounding the table of
I need to move up now and you know, so
so part of it's just
finding the place where you look like a
wonderful sweet person
in the mix.
And you mentioned
that there's this this uh dichotomy, I
guess. There's these people who are um
team players, I guess. And then there's
these people who are more pushy with
what they want and they're they're very
forthcoming. And obviously that has
benefits for their career.
I've heard people tell me that when they
want to express to their manager, "Oh, I
want to um
get promoted or something like that."
They have this feeling that they don't
want to be too pushy because it could
irk the manager. Correct. Imagine you're
a high performer is it keeps you're a
high performer but also you keep
demanding things of your manager. That
could also go wrong depending on the
manager.
I'm I'm curious like your perspective as
a as a senior leader at Amazon when you
had these demanding high performers
is that something that you were were you
happy to service their requests or was
this did ever irk you and you said, "I'm
going to actually
not give you what you want cuz you're a
little too you're a high performer but
you're also too demanding."
So I want to tell you a couple things
about that. Yes, first the great thing
about the really demanding people is if
they really are bothering you to the
point where you decide they're a net
negative if you just tell them no, they
will quit.
Because they they are so driven about
getting what they want that if you deny
them what they want
your problem will go away shortly. They
will even leave for a lesser job just
because they believe
"Well, at this place I'm going to have
different results." So yeah, you you can
calculate and say, "Okay, what There is
some calculus that says what answer gets
me the result I want." And if someone's
too pushy and not enough value, telling
them no you can't have that, they will
then go away.
The second thing though is I tended to
try and make a deal.
I'm a huge believer in deal making and I
made these deals with my own leadership,
too.
And the deal essentially was, "Okay, you
want this thing. I will help you get it.
But
you're a high performer
you're going to show incredible
performance on the things I need.
And then I will deliver."
And
uh
There are managers of course who make
that deal and don't follow through. I
can say with uh
total pride that I feel I always
followed through.
There's actually one exception early in
my career I've shared where I failed to
do that and I still feel bad about it 20
20 years later. But
um
I make a deal where I say, "Okay, you
want this. Here's what it's going to
take. I need this and this and this." So
as an example I can give you.
My manager gave me a requirement I
really didn't like. He was my vice
president. I was a director at the time
and he told me, "Your team is too
expensive. We need to put a bunch of it
offshore in India with cheaper labor.
You need to open Well, he didn't even
say India. He said, "You need to open a
low-cost offshore dev center."
And of course I didn't want to do any of
that. Like that meant traveling around
the world and having teams around the
world and I didn't know how to do it and
where to do it. He left it completely
you know, he made the whole problem
mine. He didn't say go to India. He
said, "Go somewhere."
And so the long and short of this is I
found a senior manager I knew who wanted
to get to director.
He was Indian living in the US and I
went and said, "Hey would you go back to
India and start this dev center? If you
can build me a dev center in India, I
think we can use that as a platform to
get you to director."
And that's exactly what happened. He
moved home to India. He got to take his
son home to learn Hindi and see his
grandparents. He moved to India for 3
years and during that
I was then able to use his independent
action there and the fact he was doing
all this stuff remotely and to the point
of narrative, I was able to create a
story about how this was clearly a
director level accomplishment and he was
promoted to director. But I made that
deal years before it happened. You go to
India, I will get you to director.
So
that's what I try and do with the the
demanding people.
Well, I can imagine
also that a lot of things could change
over the course of a few years. Maybe
you're at a at a different org and you
had that guy went to India and then
you're in and he's no longer reporting
to you 2 years later and you can't
deliver on that. But I mean you can't
make decisions based off that. No, if I
had been reorged or fired, you know, it
depends. Right. Right? Like there are
things that could have happened
where I would have had to say to him
"Look, I'll do what I can to support you
from the new role, but
it isn't I didn't do what I was saying.
I it's that I no longer have the power
to." And I could feel all right about
that. I can't immediately think of a
circumstance where that happened to me
where I wasn't able to follow through
for someone. Uh
but
I can see where that would happen. The
good news is people are
most leaders are professionals in that
they under they can see the difference
between
you didn't come through and
you know, happened. Those are two
different categories.
Yeah, it's interesting how much back of
the envelope
I guess deals there can be between
managers and reports or I'm sure between
managers as well, like maybe
let's say you're trying to get someone
promoted in your org and you're working
with your manager on making that happen
eventually and he says he or she says
um
okay, I have someone who's even more
urgent now, but that one's going to
happen in two halves. This one we're
going to do next half and there's all
this uh
you know, back of the envelope stuff
inside of the the manager and the
leaders
heads. There's absolutely a line.
Meaning by a line I mean a line up, a
queue.
Uh where
even HR has a policy in big companies to
say what is the forward-looking slate is
what we called it, the forward-looking
slate of promotions. And they would
track and say
by halves, who's in 6 months, 12 months,
18 months, maybe as far as 24 and you
could list different names. And so there
was a sense of like whose turn is it?
We're going to do not that there was in
my time a quota.
I understand for example at Google today
uh talking to someone I coached there,
there's a strict quota, like this
quarter or this half
two people can get from L8 to L9 in this
org.
And you know, the guy I was coaching is
like, I think I'm number four, I'm not
going to make it.
And
again, that can be toxic a little bit,
but people understand the idea of
there's a line. And so absolutely you
have those discussions. Now again
for early in your career, there's
usually no quota to go from like
entry-level college engineer or whatever
that's called where you're at to sort of
regular, you know, engineer engineer,
maybe even to senior engineer. Things
get to have more of this quota system
when the positions are rare and
expensive and there is a question
how many staff or principal engineers
does this company need? How many
distinguished engineers does it need? By
the way, those positions cost a million
dollars a piece, so we don't just want
to
hand them out like popcorn. So you
mentioned when we were talking about um
empire building,
there's this notion that managers'
career progression is tied to the number
of their recursive reports. And so
the on the one hand, there's an
incentive for managers to say
I want more new head count. But I could
also see there being cases where
managers want existing head count. So
maybe
someone underneath you is vying to take
reports from someone else and basically
steal scope for their own promotion. And
as since you were such a senior leader
at Amazon, I'm curious like how did you
handle cases where you noticed somewhere
in your org someone is trying to steal
scope from someone else in your org?
So first I would say this has become
more common as growth has slowed.
In other words, when a company is
growing very quickly as Amazon was
through much of my tenure there you see
less of this because it's easier to go
get new people than it is to fight with
someone and it causes less bad blood.
Uh not that I
never saw that. But now that companies
aren't growing, you know, if you look at
the magnificent seven or however you
look at them, most of them are flat head
count, couple exceptions
there's a lot more of this what I would
call cannibalism. Since I can't go out
and get new, I'm going to have to eat
what's here and that that's very
cannibalistic.
You see a lot of maneuvering for that.
How did I deal with it?
You can't allow
people on your team to go rogue and be
pirates in your own organization, like
capture somebody else's ship and
>> [laughter]
>> you know, kill the captain, sail away
because of what it's going to do to your
org. It it you're no longer in charge
then they're in charge, right? They're
raiding and pillaging and you seem
clueless. So you can't allow that.
But what you then have to do is either
find them a path, convince them to wait
or frankly, if they turn too septic they
become your answer. Meaning they're
going to leave or you get them to leave
and you give their team away. So if it
really is cannibalistic, what happens is
if they don't pull off, you know, it's
it's like any coup attempt, I guess in
in like politics. If you attempt a coup
and you win, you get to be president or
you know, whatever. And if you fail, you
get hung or shot. And so this is a
little bit, yeah, it's not quite that
bloody,
but
uh one thing that holds back the worst
behavior is people do realize
if I get caught being too obviously
self-serving
it's going to burn me here.
And so they usually are pretty careful.
Um but do they want it? Sure, people all
the time are asking, could I take over
this? Could I take over that? What I
encourage people to do
is I tell them, look, you never know
when a reorg's coming, you never know
when somebody's going to quit or get
fired or laid off.
So talk to your manager and say, hey
if we have an org change and there's an
opening, I just want you to know I'm
ready to step up. I'm interested.
And I will stand by you. This is one
thing people want to know in a reorg is
reorgs shake the ship and so some people
are like, oh, this company's going down
or it's not stable, I'm going to quit if
I can. If you tell your manager what
they don't want to do is put someone in
a role who's then going to leave. And so
you tell them, look
I'm actually looking to stay. So when
you need a stable leader, think of me.
And then when that opening comes up,
they're like, oh right, Ryan said he'd
stay. Perfect. Ryan Ryan just became
most qualified, not because he's best,
but because he's most reliable. Right. I
see.
>> And that is best in in my situation.
So that's what and what you just
recommended there to me almost sounds
like um a better narrative for asking
for scope. Of course.
>> Yeah, it's I mean rather than saying
give Give me this
>> Give give me this person's team. You can
say I I want what's best for the org and
if I need to step up, I'm here, but uh
without being the pirate and you might
actually get what you want. Absolutely.
And
that other piece of the messaging you
stumbled on is really important. Which
is
of course we know you want this so that
your org is bigger and so that you have
career growth. But you there's a polite
fiction
that can be true, which is I also want
what is best for the org. In other
words, I understand that my best path up
is to do things that are valuable to you
and to the organization.
And if I tell you
look
when a reorg happens, doesn't matter
what the team is, if you have a need,
I'll be there for you.
That sounds very selfless and
org-centric, even though the underlying
message could be phrased as, I don't
really care which team's available, I
just want more scope, I'll take whatever
you have. But the way I phrased it
sounds so much better cuz one sounds
like the pirate ship and the other one
sounds like the selfless servant, but
they're both really, hey, whatever's
available, I'll take it.
That that phrase you said, the the
polite fiction. I feel like that's the
thing that I could feel as while we're
talking about it, too. It's like if it
feels weird, it feels uncomfortable, it
feels conniving almost cuz it's it's
it's uh
you have you secretly you have this and
also everyone else knows you have this.
But you say this, but you I mean both
can be true. That's that's yeah. That's
the key is
it can be conniving.
But it doesn't have to be. They can be
honest. I can go to my manager and say,
look, I want to grow and I will do
whatever you need in order to grow. Like
whatever's available, I will take it and
do my utter best on it. And that that
can be both things.
One story, when I was a director working
my way towards VP
I once again had been put under a VP who
had no other engineering leaders.
But then they kept giving him more
engineering stuff and I was the first
and I built trust with him. And he just
automatically came to me with
everything, like, well, they handed me
this, can you take it?
And at one point I was managing, I think
eight different functions. And they were
as diverse
all over the place. I'll give you three
examples.
I led
the technical team for reverse
logistics, meaning when people traded in
video game cartridges, we had to grade
them and sell them used.
I was an advisor to the team that was
grading returned video games or or used
video games.
I was
selling new video games, like software
downloads, video game downloads. And
then uh
I was um
starting to build Amazon's Appstore.
That's three examples. A fourth example
is I also owned our B2B business where
like Amazon was trying to displace and
go into the market of Office Depot and
like ship pallets of paper to people.
And these all had ended up under my
boss. I had this
you know, you call it whatever you want,
but this random mixture of stuff.
But my boss loved it and over time that
totaled 200 people from all these
different functions.
Um and that just came from saying yes to
everything. Now, did I really want to
work on grading video games or shipping
pallets of paper to schools? Not really.
So
it was the win-win though. Well, this
reminds me of the offshore India story
that you had, which is your
manager has work he doesn't want to do,
and so he will pass it to you cuz he's
identified you as the high performer
that'll solve his problem. So,
it is win-win for you because you wanted
the larger org, and
he's does not want to deal with these
problems.
>> Exactly. And so, someone I really
respect, he's now a senior vice
president uh at Walmart,
he he said he was taught in turn by a a
senior vice president at Amazon,
the simple way to get promoted is quote,
"Solve problems for your boss."
Like, if you just need to get it down to
five words,
solve problems for your boss.
If you're solving their problems, they
will value you. And if they value you,
if you then express what you would like,
they don't want to lose you because not
everyone's helping them that way. Most
Most people are not. They're just
punching the clock or fighting to do
their own things. And so, even a
so-called bad boss will often take care
of someone who's helping them because
even if their calculus is,
"Well, imagine I'm evil and I don't
really care about anybody but myself,
but I've got this team of people, and
some of them are helping me, and some of
them aren't. Who do I want to keep? Even
if I'm totally selfish, I want to keep
the ones that are helping me. So, even
then it can work out."
What about the case where
cuz in engineering, there are cases
where we can create scope where someone
goes off, they they find a problem that
we didn't know existed, and they build a
new system that changes the industry or
does something really impressive, and
then
the impact they had is just incredible.
>> Mhm. But they didn't necessarily solve a
problem that that boss specifically came
to them with.
>> Sure.
Um
that could also work though as well. And
the man- And that manager would push
that promo through.
Um but I guess that's a different Well,
path.
Um and I I recommend both of these. What
I mean is,
ask your manager what you can do, how
you can help them, but also be thinking
about what can you do on your own, or
what can you go to your manager and say,
"I think we should do this, and here's
why."
So, an example I'll give,
uh Amazon now sells over a billion
dollars a year of funny t-shirts, custom
printed, you know, you can
put your slogan on a t-shirt and put it
up on Amazon and buy it or sell for or
get other people to do it. I helped
start that business, and specifically,
I funded the initial team on it. And my
manager was saying, "Hey, you run the
Amazon's app store. Like, what does that
have to do with t-shirt printing? This
has nothing to do with it.
Why are you doing this?" I said, "Well,
I think there's a big business here.
But,
I need 10 people, and I have 800. So, if
you're going to tell me that I can't
spend basically 1% of my resources on
this thing I believe in, we have another
discussion to have cuz you're
micromanaging me. Like,
this should be within And so, he's like,
"Fine.
I disagree, but go do You're right, it's
only a few people. Go do your thing."
And then it turned into a big business.
Um and of course, I'm simplifying a ton
when I say, "And then it turned into a
big business." There were like years of
work in that phrase.
>> But,
I
was thinking about what else can I do?
What else makes sense that either with
my own resources or with lightweight
approval, I can go work on.
And so, I think with your manager, of
course you're trying to ask what do they
need?
And that's what I was doing with 790 out
of my 800 team.
And 10, I was doing something that
he didn't think was a good idea, but I
was able to say like, "Well, let me have
my 10."
He's like, "All right, that, you know,
you're a big enough leader if
you know, you're now responsible for
making these people useful."
So, he did.
And if I failed, I started projects that
also didn't work out, you've got to shut
them down quickly, and, you know, have a
good enough hit rate.
But,
I think there's multiple paths to the
top. I tried them all, right? Be be the
helpful person, but also be the
inventor.
We talked about reorgs earlier, and
you you mentioned that it can be used to
manage certain leaders out.
>> Sure.
What is that What does that look like in
practice? Like, can you give me an
example?
Well, what it looks like in practice is
you put them on something they don't
want to work on, and you claim well,
that was the only seat. That was the
seat we needed you in.
I mean, it's I I'd like to claim it's
more complicated than that, but
um
I'll tell a story of someone who got
reorged, and I thought they'd quit.
Uh so much the the manager even thought
they were going to quit, uh
and was very upset with this.
When I first joined Amazon, we had a few
groups,
and we organized ourselves, and I owned
what was going to be Prime Video,
and someone else owned what became Prime
Music, and a third person owned what
became the Kindle, the e-reader.
And then there was a guy who had a clear
ownership over the ingestion pipeline.
So, the way to digitize movies, music,
etc. was all a unified pipeline.
And then there was one more leader,
and he got given
database maintenance,
quality assurance,
and like a couple small things. And even
he joked, "Well, my group's other.
>> [snorts]
>> It's It's the garbage can, right?"
And our our VP was like, "Don't call it
that. You cannot call it that. What
about the people in it?" Like,
and I'm sure he was thinking like the
leader who stuck with other isn't going
to stick around. Well, as far as I know,
that guy is still at Amazon 20 years
later
because he was one of those very calm,
nice guys who was willing to do what was
needed. He was the team player who was
going to do what was needed.
Um
but the point is, if I wanted to get rid
of a high performer,
not a high performer, why would I want
to get rid of a high performer? But if I
wanted to get rid of a pushy, overly
ambitious person,
just give them other.
Like, 6 weeks later, that's a vacancy. I
can open the role right now, right?
[laughter] Cuz like, I'm a bit of a
confrontational person. So, when I
needed to fire someone, I tended to just
go straight at it.
But this putting someone in a seat they
don't like is classic.
And there's even a um
this is a widely understood You know,
this isn't an Amazon thing. If you go to
Japanese culture, completely other
country, there's this concept called a
window seat. I don't know if you've ever
heard of this. Mhm.
So, in Japanese culture, which is very
collectivist, and I'm not an expert, so
maybe someone from Japan will say this
isn't true, but I don't think so.
Uh
you want to be in the center of the
building. Even though window seats are
very desirable in American culture, the
hot You want to be in the middle of
things there. You want to be close to
the CEO and close to the action.
So, actually being on a window means
you're not that important.
And so, ironically, what we would think
of as great, being given a corner
office,
in Japan is a signal of you've been
moved as far from what's happening as
possible.
You've been You've been exiled to the
land of irrelevance, where you you know,
you're not a You don't even co-workers
on one side, you have glass. And that
would be a way to signal to somebody
like, "Your career here is now over.
You're in a window seat." So, this idea
isn't um
you know, I don't think it's Some people
would think, "Oh, well, that's only
Amazon because they have a history of
being combative." I don't think that's
true. I think this idea is well known.
You mentioned that that one guy who gets
other, or the garbage can, he's uh
the nicest guy, or he's he's the team
player, and this and that. And I I guess
I see the incentive structure that makes
it that nice guy gets garbage can. But,
why I don't know, some part of me is
wishing the world wasn't that way. Sure.
Is it possible to build an org where if
you're you're nice, and you wait your
turn, that the Because you're you could
choose as like as the VP, you could say,
"I'm going to reward
the nice people that don't pressure."
You can to some degree.
Um first, note that the org I described
where I had all those random things was
also the garbage can, so I built the
garbage can kind of opting into it.
Like, I will take all of your junk, and
that is my role. He was not doing that
in the same way, but there was some of
that.
Uh the problem with only rewarding the
nice guys
is number one,
sometimes the nice folks don't actually
want more.
In other words,
ambition tends to come out, and if
people are really ambitious, they do
usually end up not always, but they
usually end up more vocal.
Second though,
I have the problem that I do have all
these vocal people,
and
what they're going to do usually
is not become less vocal just because I
have an example of play nice and you'll
move up. They're going to look for where
can I go that's going to reward me right
away.
And so,
of course,
maybe a better leader than I can build
this culture where all the nice people
are rewarded, and all the sort of less
nice people see the
see the error of their ways and become
naturally generous,
but I've just That isn't human nature.
And so, I think there is some balancing.
What I often do, as you heard from my
coaching, and I'll be honest, is I tell
the nice folks,
"Being that nice isn't helping you. You
don't have to be a jerk. You have to do
what I did where you say
my career is very important to me.
It's okay. It's okay to have
Where people fall down is they come
particularly in tech
from non-US cultures that are
collectivist or have different mores and
we're asking for what you want or
speaking up
culturally doesn't fit.
I see this a lot particularly with women
from Asia, different parts of Asia.
At home they're expected culturally to
take one role which is often more family
oriented and supporting of parents and
grandparents and so on. But then to get
ahead in work they need to be a little
bit more outspoken and it's a big
contrast.
Um
I would just say it's okay to ask for
what you want. That isn't
that isn't wrong.
And
managers
even good managers, they're not in the
business of guessing.
If you've never told me what you want
sure in theory I should ask you but I'm
very busy and so sometimes I get around
to that and sometimes I don't. Meanwhile
this other person, you know, every 3
days is knocking on my door. I'm super
clear on what they want. When it comes
to engineers, there's one one layer to
think of and so if someone's low
performing, they may be your peer. But
if you have a low performing manager,
there's this there's this vertical
stacking that we have.
You might be reporting to someone who
you think is not great at their job and
so the natural thought is go to their
manager which would be your skip. Which
I guess you could consider this as
mutiny if you went to them and you said,
"Hey,
my manager is bad. I don't want to
report to this person.
Do you have any examples of of this kind
of escalation coming to you or someone
in your recursive chain was considered
incompetent by their reports and they
came directly to you and they said,
"Please manage this person out or
I just don't want to report to this
person." All the time.
All the time.
One of the hardest things for
people to understand is I've identified
a legitimate weakness in my boss. I go
to my skip, why doesn't he do something?
Well, if you come to me with a weakness
in one of my employees
there is
subconsciously this process that goes on
that says, "I have two choices.
I can believe that you're overly
sensitive and high maintenance.
In which case I don't really have a
problem. You're the problem.
And you know, you're two levels down for
me so if you quit, the manager has to do
the backfill.
And I can tell the manager, you know,
Ryan was here. He said this that and the
other. Maybe you can work with him.
And that's exactly what you don't want
is me ratting you out but I can make it
my manager's problem.
On the other hand, if I agree with you
and I'm like, you know what this this
manager I have really isn't that good.
Now I have three problems.
This is really bad for me. One,
I have to decide what to do with my
manager. Maybe I have to manage them
out.
Two, if I do manage them out, I have to
hire and train somebody else. And three,
while they're gone, I have to do all
their work myself.
So you can see why even if it's
subconscious, I have a lot of reasons
not to listen
or not to believe very easily. So,
mutiny. Let's talk about mutiny.
Uh if you want to see it as a mutiny,
we've talked about pirates already.
Never mutiny alone.
If you want that to work, if you really
want to say this manager is bad and we
have a problem
take two or three people or send two or
three people in sequence. Find some of
your coworkers who are willing to speak
up because I will give you an example.
It really bothers me. I had a leader
who was
treating the women on his team like
crap.
Now he wasn't doing that in front of me
but it turns out it was true.
Well,
it took a long time
for the different rumors to bubble up to
me enough to where I'm like, "I'm
hearing bad things." And then I went and
talked to several of the women and like,
"So, in working with this person I'm
hearing" and they're like, "Oh, yeah."
Well then I was like, "Oh, okay, I've
been blind to a problem. I need to act
on it."
Had any one of them come to me early and
said, "This person's a problem. They're
doing this that and the other." I
probably wouldn't have listened
because it was a lone report. But when
several of those reports came up then
I'm like, "Oh, I've been missing
something." So if you want to hold a
mutiny, go together. Right? Like even if
it's Zelda, like it's it's dangerous to
go alone, take this. Take other people.
I see. Okay, so if if let's say there's
a high performing IC Yeah.
>> who is reporting to a manager and say
the fact is that that manager has some
shortcomings in in their abilities.
You would say don't go immediately to
the skip. First
build allies with some of the other
people and say, "Hey, are you also
seeing this with this person?" And If
you can. Yeah, you want to talk to them
and say, "Hey, do you see what I see?"
Well, one thing is that's a way to
sanity check.
I'm really struggling with our boss in
this area.
Do you Are you having that problem?
And if they say, "No, I get along with
him great and here's how." Then maybe
you can learn and adjust. That's the
style thing. Whereas if they're like,
"Oh, yeah."
Then the hardest next hurdle is are they
willing to speak up?
Cuz a lot of people aren't. But
if they know that you're going to go
first and play ringleader. Like I will
go and talk to our skip but I'm going to
tell our skip they can verify my story
by talking to you or and and also to
Sally or Fred or Rajiv.
Most managers, if you go to them and
say, "Look,
I know that my saying the boss is a weak
link is uncomfortable and difficult for
you
but
these three people are all willing to
share similar stories. Would you
consider at least talking to them?"
Most managers will do that. Most, you
know, not all. There's no There's no
guarantees when you're dealing with
people. I mean that's Yeah, that's the
immediate thing I imagine is let's say I
was that IC and then I went to other
people and we all kind of knew that that
person had a shortcoming.
It
there's the difference between that that
water cooler talk and saying, "Yeah,
this person is disorganized. Oh, yeah,
he keeps doing that."
Compared to hey, I'm going to go to his
boss now and we're going to we're going
to make take this up a notch because
also there's this this delicate balance
which is all these people still report
to that person. So now if you were to
get caught at any point in this process,
you might worry about retribution or
something if you're wrong. Um what about
the path of cuz that this is a this is a
lot. I mean your manager needs to be
pretty bad if you do this.
What about the approach of you say,
"Hey, it's just me and him." And you
want to go to the skip and say, "Hey,
Ethan, um
you know, nothing nothing personal with
the person that I'm reporting to
but I see uh
better business case for me to go to
another team or you know, something like
that where you were to say I
you know, don't don't think poorly of
this manager but I'll be more productive
somewhere else for your org." What about
that approach rather than the the whole
mutiny
>> two approaches.
Um
the first is which is
remember we talked about
the story you tell versus the story that
may be true. If you can actually make a
strong case that you're equally valuable
or more valuable somewhere else, a
plausible case, don't even bring up the
manager.
Just say, "Hey, I was looking at this
other role and I think I could do so
much more for you in the org over here
because of A, B, and C."
And you try that run first and if that
works, you're done. You never have to
bring it up.
The second thing you can say, you've
just you've got to you've got to play
chess not checkers meaning several moves
in advance. You can totally say, "Look,
candidly
you keep it blame free.
I'm not compatible
with
our leader. I'm not Maybe it's him,
maybe it's me. Of course I naturally
feel that maybe I'm doing good work and
and he could improve but I'm not here to
throw your manager under the bus. I'm
just here to tell you I need a change."
And I did this once with a leader at
Amazon where I wanted to make a change.
I was doing a good job for him in the
role I was in so he wanted me to stay
there.
And what I had to help him understand is
I said,
"You are seeing this
as I take this new role
or I stay in this role and you'd prefer
I stay in this role because that's good
for you and I get that.
But what I'm trying to tell you is
either I take this new role in your org
that I'm asking for
or I'm going somewhere else entirely. So
there is no choice keep me where I'm at.
There's do you want me on your team or
on someone else's team. Now I had both
options available
and it was really interesting because
after weeks and weeks of resistance, I
was in the new role the next morning.
Like once he got the clarity of oh, I
thought I had a choice between you stay
in the role I want you in
and you go to the role I don't really
want you in.
But the choice I actually have is I keep
you in my team or I lose you.
It was totally different the next
morning.
But how how did you word that in a way
where that person you were reporting to
did not feel upset that you kind of
subverted their power and forced their
hand.
Um that's a good question and so I can
exemplify that. I framed it in terms of
what they would do.
Uh this person was a vice president. At
that point I was a vice president
reporting to them. So I was like a
smaller vice president, whatever, lower
in level.
And I had gotten a job offer from a
senior vice president in a different
organization.
That was my other job. So I went to him
and I said, "I have an offer
from this SVP.
Now you know
that if I give my word to that guy, I
have to go. Like that's what you would
do. If I give my word, it's over.
You know I really want this other role.
I have to give this guy an answer.
You've told me no on this other role
several times. What do you want me to
do?"
Bam, the door like cuz once he
understood, he understood
he would never break his word to an SVP.
So he understood that the moment I gave
my word,
it was done.
And so
that's the same like what would you do?
If you can tap into the manager feeling
like, "Okay, I don't like it, but I get
it." That's what I was doing is he was
like, "Oh, I don't like this, but okay,
I get it." There were three roles that
under consideration.
>> was the one I was in, the one I really
wanted, and the alternative I had gotten
on the table.
>> So you brought in a a new option that
was better than your current and you
said, "My alternative now is I may leave
you unless you give me what I want."
>> Yeah, but you didn't say that directly.
>> what I want. Instead I said, I actually
I'm very careful not to make it that
threatening. I said,
"You know once I give my word I'm I
can't go back on that." Like
that's
The the the wording it I I mean as soon
as you say I think I mean
if I was that manager I got I there's
I'm on your side even though I see the
what was the what was the word there?
The polite fiction, I guess. I see the
polite fiction immediately, but and I
laugh cuz it's just so
And I think this is a skill I haven't
figured out how to teach people, but
maybe this talk can help.
Several times I've given you these
polite fictions, these careful wordings.
I think a mistake people make that they
can do so much better is think through
your wording before you're in the room
because most of these conversations are
not spur of the moment. You either
they're either on the calendar. This is
my performance review or whatever.
Or
you at least know they're going to come
up. And so spend the time to have that
key phrase ready so that you can just
with
true sincerity
say
"Yeah, you know once I give my word, I
can't go back on that."
And
I deliver that, I look like
I did mean it. In no way was I lying.
But at the same time I deliver it like
I'm an angel just fallen from heaven.
You know
poor innocent victim. Both are true. And
when I put the screws to that other boss
long ago and said, "Well, I'm going to
have to consider if my career is not as
important to Amazon as it is to me, I'm
going to have to think about that."
Again, I said that with a warm smile
like, "Hey,
of course I'm going to have to think
about that." And I just look like the
kitten, you know, the anime kitten with
the giant eyes.
Well, body language matters because if I
say that to you, see I can say that
differently. I can say, "Well, Ryan,
you know, if my career is not as
important to Amazon as it is to me, I'm
going to have to think about that."
Then [snorts] they're like, "Well, screw
you."
Whereas I say, "Well, of course I'm
going to have to think about what that
means for me."
Totally different delivery, same lines,
same words. Now, there's some people
watching this, engineers who are like,
"I hate you. I hate the politics." I
hear you, but this is human nature and
human interaction. You're dealing with
other humans and their emotions are at
play and their defensiveness and their
own stress.
Do yourself a favor and get good at
this.
Well, and yeah, and to me that that is
clearly your superpower. I mean
I can imagine so many other people in
these situations not getting the
outcomes they want because they worded
slightly differently and it doesn't come
off you know, the the way they say it
and and kind of the
the the the interplay about what that
person wants and you know, the things
that you could say. And how do you do
that? Like if we were to try to reverse
engineer like coming up with those
polite fictions so that people can get
more of what they want out of their
careers. I I imagine this would be
useful even outside of Well, it's all
through your life.
>> Yeah, all throughout your life.
>> it's all any any negotiation, any deal
making
um
I call it I've tried to reverse engineer
and we'll do some more right here right
now.
I call it being interpersonally warm.
So being friendly, smiling, not getting
agitated while being professionally
firm.
Saying what I need to about what I
really want but in a way where I don't
bring anger or
you versus me into it as much as I can.
And so
um
there are some key phrases.
Uh a great phrase is help.
Right? How How can you help me?
I I want to get to the next level.
How can you help me? Because
everyone loves to think of themselves as
helpful.
And so if I ask you for help,
you know, that that's just a as opposed
to I ask, "What are you going to do for
me?"
It's that sort of phrasing.
Um so part of it is the attitude. I read
a book I really love. I can share the
book. It's called Leadership and
Self-Deception.
Uh and it's written by some research
institute called The Arbinger Institute.
But what makes this book so interesting
and what it taught me
is
don't see the other person as an
obstacle to what you want.
See them as a human being trying to do
the best they can in their situation who
has all kinds of problems.
And what makes a huge difference here is
when I start seeing my boss who I want
something from not as well this person
controls my pay or my promotion and I
have to yank it out of them. That's
seeing them as a thing. They're an
obstacle like a barrier across the road.
If I see them as a human trying to get
by, then I can
emote to them and say, "Look,
here's what I need.
What do you need so we can make this
work? I want to help you because I want
your help." And that's an honest offer
most people can understand. And so
it comes from that
how do I see them? I think this is a
huge thing is
we objectify others.
This happens anytime you're working with
another team as an engineer you do this
all the time. I just need them to do
this thing. How can I your thought is
how can I get them to do this thing?
That's making them an object. I need to
give you the right inputs and yank on
the right levers so that the right thing
comes out. I'm treating them like an
API. I make the right call, I get the
right result.
What you want to do is treat them like a
person and say, "Look, I know you have a
busy road map
and I understand you have a lot of
pressures.
But I do need this. So what can we do
together? How can I help you so that you
can make the time or let me make this
change myself?"
And the key is
once people feel
like you're caring about them as a
person, they usually respond that way.
Now,
nothing works 100% of the time.
And I can't instantly recall one, but
I've probably
rolled out these polite phrases before
and not won. Like I
um I was debating politics with my
college roommate and I thought to
myself, this is very recent.
I'm going to use all I teach all day
about how smooth I am and how
influential I am. I'm going to use all
my skills and I'm going to convince him
of this point in modern American
politics which is very contentious. I
failed.
But the best I can say is that we left
the conversation nobody angry.
Friendly.
But I I kind of got nowhere because
sometimes
sometimes their motives and what's
important to them
just can't be aligned with yours. So I'm
not My only point here is
these techniques will get you way more
success. I don't want to convince
anybody
that like I have some magic recipe
that's 100% likely to always work out.
You said
a few things and it sounds like you had
some high-level
rules you could you could give, but it's
hard to reverse engineer because it's
it's not a recipe. Inevitably it's
it's two people interacting and every
single person's different and seems like
the the unifying thing is to really
imagine what is that person feeling and
when you say things to them?
What do they want and how will how you
present yourself make them feel in the
exchange and hopefully that goes in the
direction you want.
But obviously not always cuz it's
subjective and you can miscalculate. So,
I think an analogy that may work for at
least people who know chess a little bit
about chess
is I think of this a little bit like
I'm not an expert chess player.
But I understand
there's two pieces to playing chess
well. One is of course knowing the board
and how to move. The other is called a
book opening where you've memorized a
set of opening moves. And I think what
you can do in a lot of these
conversations
is
open with a set of pre-planned moves
where you've thought about how am I
going to make my first ask?
And you've thought about uh when am I
going to do it? Like don't catch your
manager wanting to have a deep
conversation about career 5 minutes
after
a high severity problem on a Friday.
Like they're not in the mindset, right?
If their hair's on fire and they're
trying to get out the door to pick up
their kids, this is not when you're
going to get the best hearing. So
in the play chess analogy, set up your
opening moves, but then yes, at some
point there are some general rules about
chess. Again, I'm no expert, but like in
chess you want to hold the middle of the
board. Being towards the middle is So,
if you have a chance to move towards the
middle, move towards the middle. Well,
with a manager or any leader that you
want something from
try to move towards that common ground
where we can agree.
But yeah, it's about learning how to
play well.
Um
and I've spent a career
learning how to play well in verbal
conversation.
And I think the biggest thing I used to
have quite a temper.
I actually got fired two separate times,
put on layoff list because I was
volatile and critical early in my
career.
I put the temper away and I I learned
how not to go there.
And that made a huge difference because
people don't react well to anger or
criticism, right? Even if you're right.
So, I mean obviously you're very adept
at this interpersonal uh way to
influence people.
>> Mhm.
When you were working in corporate
America and you met someone else who you
identified had that skill set, let's say
it's some manager underneath you or
maybe managers in other orgs or could be
an engineer as well. Yep. Is that
something that in your mind that's a
positive thing or is that something
where you're thinking I have to be
careful cuz that person can mold things
around them strongly?
Both. What you're trying to do next is
assess what's their motive.
People often ask me, what's the
difference between influence and
politics? Like when does influence
become politics or manipulation?
And for me the answer is the skill sets
are the same, they're around motive.
And so, one thing I teach executive
presence.
And one thing I point out about
executive presence is Darth Vader had it
in spades. Like he had tons of executive
presence and so did Palpatine, right?
They're these powerful commanding
figures.
These skills, being influential can be
used for good or evil.
So, with the example you're talking
about, the thing I'm now trying to
figure out is okay, this person is a
skilled operator.
You know, are they US special forces or
are they Russian special forces, right?
Like like which side, you know, who am I
dealing with here, right?
Am I am I dealing with someone who's got
to like rescue me and get me out of a
hostage situation or am I dealing with
someone who's across the line and is
about to drop a bomb on me?
And
so
I'm trying to figure out motive.
And um there's kind of three cases even
there. There's people whose motive is to
do good, easy to work with, great. We
both have high social skill, we're going
to be so effective together.
There's people who are completely out
for themselves. Now, you know, going
back to Star Wars, it's very much like
Sith versus Jedi. I've got to get my
lightsaber up and I'm going to be
fighting for my life.
And then there's this middle ground
though that's interesting which is
well, this person
has motives I can work with. They're not
altruistic, they're not just trying to
do well, but in this case
they kind of want what I want or I can
give them enough wins and I can
negotiate I can
be like, hey, you want this, I want that
and that's the deal making of of
we're never going to be best friends. I
don't necessarily think you're
the best person
but in this limited scope
we can both make money together or we
can both ship something together.
Let's say there's someone who is
extreme high performer but you can tell
they they will only do what will help
them.
And you see a path to aligning what you
both want so it can be good.
But you could tell that if this is ever
off their path they will not be on your
side or in fact if there's something
that could get them ahead and put you
behind, they would gladly do it. Would
you still choose to ally with that
person or would you kind of separate
them from you and your org somewhere?
Well, if I could separate, I'd love to.
But remember at work we don't get to
choose always the teams we work with.
Like sometimes we need another team.
Sometimes we need a team that's
run by a terrible person, sometimes we
need a team that's run by a
self-serving person.
I think
if you want to succeed in your career
most
sure, get away or marginalize or or
minimize contact with difficult or
unethical people.
But also learn to work
even with the very unethical
because sometimes you're going to have
to.
Now, of course there's a limit. I'm not
saying break laws or do thing you know,
but
um
but sometimes you don't get to choose
who your teammates are or what system
you need. And so, I do think it's worth
being equipped.
How am I going to do the best I can? And
there are there's we don't have time.
There's a lot of techniques to protect
yourself. There's bring allies with you.
For example, most slippery people
they love to be slippery in the dark
where they're not going to get caught.
So, if you can
bring a few allies so it looks like, oh
everyone thinks this.
Often suddenly they'll say, "Oh, I think
that too."
Because they you know, part of their
power is
slippery people
usually can't afford to have everyone
know
that they're unethical. Because
once we know once everyone knows
someone's unethical, they do get
shunned.
And and so they have to keep it largely
under wraps or
defensible.
Uh what there's a phrase from politics
called plausibly deniable where they can
deny that they were really as bad as
maybe you're saying.
What you want to do is put them in a
situation where it's easier to go along
with you
than to fight you.
So, construct a situation where they're
like okay, this isn't the best for me.
Like I'd rather stab Ethan in the back,
but boy there's a lot of witnesses.
Right? That's And so you
And it's unfortunate, you know, again, I
know many engineers will be frustrated,
why do I have to do all this crap? Can't
I just do good work? Why why?
Sorry, humanity. Going back by the way,
read any, you know, ancient text of
philosophy or religion, humans haven't
changed. They've been mean to each other
since the first ape clubbed the other
ape.
This doesn't change. So, it's I'm sorry
that it frustrates you, but you're going
to have to do it. So, it sounds like the
best way to prevent yourself from from
backstabbing is to have a really strong,
I guess, soft power in your org where
there are people who will defend you or
just the setup is that you would be too
powerful for them to come after you. Not
worth it. Not worth it.
>> Right. It's it's uh
it's like all the animals in the animal
kingdom, you know, like porcupine.
All right? Plenty of animals can eat
porcupine if they're willing to get a
mouthful of quills, but it's not worth
it.
Like, you know, uh
and I'm sure there are many other
examples, but
you you you want to be not worth it.
It's just easier. Because remember, this
is important. Other than cartoons like a
Darth Vader
people don't wake up in the morning.
That slippery person does not wake up in
the morning and say, "I'm an evil jerk
and that's all I ever want to be." Their
self-narrative
is more like
I'm doing what I need to. I'm practical.
Other people are wishy-washy and have
all these optimistic things. I'm
practical. And some people get upset
that I'm so practical. Well, that's not
my fault. That's what they're telling
themselves. And so, what you want to do
is help them with their narrative and
say, "You know what? You're right,
you're very practical. And in this
situation, the practical thing
is to go ahead and help me out because
I've got a lot of support and you know,
I'm a rising star, and it's
you help me out and I'll remember.
And and they're like, oh, that is very
practical. You know, even [laughter]
though
and that that's just
it's important to remember that the
other person's narrative, we think of
them as like
that person is so unethical, they must
wake up in the morning and think about
how they can rob their grandmother.
That's not what they say about
themselves. They say, you know,
grandma's getting old, and I need her
funds because she's not really up to it
anymore, and she doesn't need all that
anyway.
But that is what they tell themselves,
right? It's not I'm a thief. What about
I mean, I think a lot of what we talked
about is kind of implying within your
org.
>> Mhm. Have you ever seen cases where
other orgs were plotting to maybe take
scope from your org or kind of
you know, battling between the org
orgs?
Oh, jeez.
I've seen this all the time.
And you know, again
the narrative people are telling
themselves is not usually I'm going to
pillage scope from that other org.
It's they know their own org and their
own mission really well. So, they have a
really clear idea why having your scope
would help them.
Meanwhile, they don't know your mission,
and they don't know everything you're
really doing. And so, it's very easy for
them to
imagine
that your org's not that important. A
very smart engineering leader once said,
respect between two engineering teams is
inversely proportional to their
distance. So, the further apart they
are, the more they belittle each other
cuz they can't see the work.
And you hear this all the time. Like, I
think of Amazon S3, right? This
service that stores now hundreds of
trillions of objects.
I've heard it described as well, it's
just a big disk drive.
So, this is very belittling. Like Like,
of course at some level it is just a big
storage system. That's true.
But the boy that I'm at, it's really
just a big disk drive.
It's so dismissive. And you see this all
the time.
And the closer you get to home, the more
you've seen the work or worked with the
people or seen the complexities and all
the edge cases, you're like, oh,
actually that is very complicated. Well,
I see this with orgs. Sure, there are
some leaders who are just like, yeah, we
should take that org cuz I want it.
But a lot of times what they're doing is
like, well, we can do so much more with
it. Again, that internal narrative.
Very few humans wake up and say, I'm
going to be evil today.
What they do is they want something, and
they construct a line of logic, which
we're very good at, about why that's
actually a great thing anyway.
And and that's where you get the org
versus org fights.
Let's say I'm an engineering leader.
Mhm. How do I protect my org from other
orgs? Uh well, first thing is you've got
to
get all um Hmm, this is the skunk trick,
I guess. We'll use animals here. The
skunk trick is make yourself
unattractive. So, trick number one is
list all the things that they don't know
about that you have to maintain that are
unsexy and they don't want. And have the
customers for those show up and say how
important they are.
Well, yeah, well, we actually run, you
know, the Yugoslavian Yugoslavia is not
even a country anymore, but we'll use
it. We run the Yugoslavian tax engine,
and so, boy, we get a lot of tickets for
that, and it's going to have to be
owned. So, are you guys ready to take on
that? That's one thing you can do. The
other thing is
um
you want to make yourself thorny. Again,
there is a little bit
uh
who's the least attractive target? And
so, they're out sort of
do they really want your org or do they
want an org? And so, one of the ways to
be thorny, honestly, is to
overreact and attack back and just make
yourself
like, oh, ouch. They They went public
and volatile really soon.
Maybe [snorts] I'll go for a softer
target.
Now, you have to be careful in how you
do that because if you
if you behave in a way that makes it
easy to discredit you, then you're an
easier target. Oh, see, Ethan's not a
very mature leader. We should definitely
move that under me. I'll I'll make sure
we don't have this sort of unseemly
behavior. That's weakening [snorts]
myself.
But if I can
immediately say counterattack and say,
you know, it's really good that you're
thinking about merging our orgs. Your
org is going to be so great as a part of
our org, and I promise I'll take care of
you.
Then they're like, ooh,
maybe maybe I, you know, messed with the
bull and got the horns. So, you can
So, there's
I you know, I'm uncomfortable talking
about sort of combative tactics because
I see when you get to that, it's a
failure
in my opinion. But
if someone's trying to maneuver, and you
don't want that,
it's a matter of shining a light on it
and sort of exposing their motives if
you can, while making a strong case for
why the work you do is very important.
Now, where you're vulnerable
is if your work is behind if if you have
weaknesses, if your work is behind, if
it's not making a lot of money, if it's
performing poorly,
those are hard cases to make. Whereas,
if you're on a strong platform of high
performance,
then you have a lot of arguments,
hopefully, about don't distract us.
Another great one is
we know reorgs causes 6-month hit in
productivity.
We're killing it on profitability, new
customers, whatever is valuable.
We should
you know, we shouldn't even talk about
this for 6 months. We need to hit these
goals and get the year end. Cuz you
know, in 6 months
they'll have moved on. So, one thing
that's another
delaying tactic. And I hope what you're
really getting from this answer is how
quickly I'm coming up with like
here's three or four different things.
You just have to look at the situation
and say,
how can I put this off, change it,
scare them off, make myself
unattractive, whatever I need to do.
I'm just looking for what's, again,
narrative. What's the best story?
People love to think that facts make
decisions.
But
but we know from psychology
people come to an emotional conclusion
and then rationalize it.
If I am a better storyteller,
I give you that narrative that you're
like, yeah, that sounds right. That
feels emotionally where you wanted it to
go,
and then you have a story. I've helped
you wrap your own story around it. And
then once it's your story, your internal
story of how this should be, it's very
hard for anyone to shake that. So, be
the better storyteller. You mentioned a
lot of tactics on defense. Uh-huh.
What about the flip side? Let's say
you're high-performing manager, and you
you see there's a great reason for
another org nearby to be absorbed into
your org. What are What are the attacker
tactics?
Well, Ryan, when you said we would just
go deep on transparency, you were not
kidding.
Uh attacker tactics.
So, the best attack
the you know, which I would argue isn't
even necessarily an attack, but it has
that effect, is
a real story of how that's going to
create more value.
If you can
make a point that, you know, whatever
whatever metric you're using, this group
puts out one release a year, I can get
it to two. This group makes $100
million, I can get it to 200. And here's
how.
Then that's actually a very good
argument.
If we go to
maybe slightly
less good arguments,
they usually have to do with seniority,
efficiency,
I can save costs. I can by consolidating
this, we're either going to get more
done with less, or
um
we're going to have simplicity in our
communication, or you're going to have
fewer direct reports, which is going to
make your life easier.
They're They're arguments that aren't
necessarily false,
but they're less directly about business
growth, and they're more about
making things smoother for the leader
who's making the decision, or nicer, or
cheaper. They're like second-order
effects.
Um
I wouldn't
I hope no one would do this, but I know
people do. The third attack tactic is
clearly
to go highlight flaws in the other org,
right? To go show, well, this leader has
this problem, and this team has this
problem, and they have high turnover,
and they have high costs, and look at
this outage.
And you're
basically trying to show, well, it's a
dumpster fire, and you should let me put
that out. But what if that's true,
though?
Okay, if it's true,
again, if it's true it's a dumpster
fire, then
you're offering to make things better.
It's where you're kind of highlighting
things that maybe aren't as bad, you
know, and just like only pointing at the
bad. Yeah, if it's if it's true an org
is struggling, the truth is you can talk
to your manager and say, look,
the way I would do that, though, is not
say I should take over them, I'll fix
them.
I would say, hey,
I go to whoever owns it
or the common boss, and I say, hey,
I can't help but notice that you're
having a lot of trouble here. Is there
anything I can do to help?
That's my opening gambit for I want to
take it over.
Because
I can go in there and start helping and
then later they're like, "Wow, it's so
much better under Ethan's leadership."
And at that point I can casually
mention, "Well, I you know, if it would
really help you."
>> [laughter]
>> You know, we could just consolidate.
Now that I'm here, I see all these
efficiencies. That's That's like another
way to go about the same thing. I feel
like giving all these answers, people
are going to think like, "Wow, that
Ethan is a real sadistic."
>> [laughter]
>> I am telling the truth.
>> is what actually happens though, I
think, like what you're saying. So, it's
kind of um I don't know.
>> I have seen it all. I have seen things,
you know, that make me want to close my
eyes, for sure. I kind of want to talk a
little bit about like uh some of that
interpersonal stuff or maybe, you know,
the backstabbing and the some of the
politics.
If there is someone within your org that
is a people problem, they're
doing something actually like I don't
know.
>> Mhm. You You can just immediately get
them fired. Cuz they're in your
recursive reports, talk to their manager
or whoever. And kind of figure it out.
>> the evidence, for sure.
But yeah, you can absolutely You can
move very quickly if it's clear. But
what if it's someone in another org? So,
another org, there's a person who is
well-liked within their org that is a
major problem for your org.
Well, then what do you do?
So,
um one of my managers had this problem
and he uh
he literally put someone in a position
he called a meat shield.
>> [laughter]
>> What?
Where it's like, "This person is a huge
pain for our org or this org. Your job
is to keep them off of us. [laughter]
And honestly, it's going to be a
terrible job, but I'll reward you later.
So, you need to like go be a meat shield
till this project's over."
And so,
>> The imagery is just
>> Yeah, I know. It's like it was, you
know, like put your back into it and let
them beat [laughter] you.
Um Oh my god.
And of course he had to He was very
honest with them of like, "That's your
role and I know it's a terrible role,
but I'll make it up to you, you know,
get us through this project. Like go
take one for the team and I'll pay you
back."
Um
But what else can you do
when someone's in another org? The first
thing,
the most important thing if you want to
try and make a change, is understand why
they're valuable to their org.
Because the reason they're
that other org, what they're not doing
is saying, "I know
we have this evil person and as long as
they're pointed at other orgs, we're
okay with them being evil." That's
probably not what they're saying. What
they They either aren't seeing it or
more likely that person, what they're
telling themselves is, "Well, they have
a little bit of sharp elbows, but they
get so much done that's valuable. It's
okay. And if people's feelings are hurt,
well, they're soft." It's kind of how
they So, you have to understand where
they're being seen as valuable.
And then what you have to do is go to
that leadership
and have one of a few discussions. Look,
we're willing to give you this value
without all this pain.
Is there a better way?
That's one way you can go about it. The
other way you can go about it is, "Look,
your guy is driving us nuts or is
mistreating us.
So, that's going to change.
Either
you're going to give us a new interface,
you're going to
You I I can't say you're going to fire
them, but you're going to move them away
from bothering us, at least.
Or we're going to stop cooperating.
Right? Like if If you're going to
inflict pain on us, we're going to
return the pain. Everything will be
late, everything will be your fault,
everything will be escalated, everything
will require six document reviews. We'll
put in place I'll spend the rest of the
day asking Chat GPT, "What is the most
policy checkpoints I could put on our
next release?" Right? Like this You can
express this How do you message that
with the right narrative without, you
know, pissing that leader off?
>> mean,
if I Okay, so that's that's my internal
narrative, I guess. That's my [laughter]
like, "All right, screw with me, I'll
screw with you back."
My external narrative would go something
like, "Dear peer of mine,
this person is really making things
difficult You know, you have this person
on your team.
I know they're a valuable member to you
and your team, but unfortunately, our
team is really struggling with them.
And I'd like to make a change.
Option one, you can
find a new interface person for us.
Option two is we're going to have to
adjust
to
distance ourselves for the sake of my
team and I think unfortunately, that
option's going to create
a lot of friction between our orgs
that really is going to take both of our
time.
And so, I don't want to take your time,
but I have to to protect my people. Some
of them are ready to leave. What would
you do if people on your team were ready
to leave? And so,
I'm going to have to take some steps and
that's going to increase bureaucracy and
take a lot more of your time and my
time.
And I'm sure there's a better way."
That's amazing cuz it's the same thing,
but you didn't
You didn't threaten or threaten All it
just uh by circumstance,
if you don't comply, your life will be
harder. But I wish it wasn't, but that's
just how it is. One thing people
underestimate is most leaders at a
certain level,
they may not have
expert social skills, but they're pretty
They got there for a reason.
They understand what they're being told.
Even if
they don't understand it consciously,
you know, they they get
They're sensitive to unspoken messages.
And they understand that I'm giving them
a chance to collaborate,
but that there's a stick up my sleeve,
right? That That I didn't come to this
with no other plan.
And part of this is also how I project,
how how you
If you look weak, like you're begging,
I don't really care what you need. But
you know, I'm presenting it as like,
"Wow, this is
This is really tragic cuz it's going to
get hard for both of us."
And
what I'm conveying there is, "Look, you
want to trade punches, that's okay. I
play ice hockey
and sometimes someone on ice will hit me
or, you know, be a little rough with me
and I'll just look at them and say,
'You know, two can do this. You This was
your freebie, you decide.' But I'm like
putting them on notice like, 'Hey, the
next time,
you know, I have two elbows also.'
>> [laughter]
>> Right? All this conversation makes me
think that let's say you're an um
engineer or someone who is reporting
some You want your your leader
to to be strong for your org cuz I can
imagine if they're not, let's say
they're they're very nice and and their
org is getting
I don't know, a lot of negative things
are happening to it.
And they just say, "Oh, that's okay, you
know, we'll deal with it as it comes and
all this stuff." The other everyone else
is going to step on them and that's
going to affect you if your manager
can't stand up for the org.
Absolutely. And I think remember your
manager, I've tried to showcase that
your manager doesn't have to be a mean
person to be firm, to be professionally
firm,
to have backbone.
They have to be skilled.
A lot of people, this is important, a
lot of people don't know how to be
socially skilled
and so, they can only say hard things
once they let themselves get angry or
upset. That's their fuel. Is if I need
to give you a hard performance message
and say, "Ryan,
you know, you've missed three dates in a
row."
I can only do that once I get internally
angry and like, "Ryan's missed three
dates. He let me down." And so, now I'm
coming at you.
I've gotten my ability to speak to you
and to say the truth
because see,
I'm afraid you're going to say, "Well, I
haven't." Or "It was my mom was sick."
Or whatever. And you're going to make it
hard for me. So, I have to be ready to
fight and some people can't do that
without first allowing themselves to be
angry.
You want a manager, ideally,
who can stand their ground because they
believe in it and because they are
willing to have confrontation. And I'm
no master at this, okay? I plenty of
friends will tell me where I've been a
jerk.
But I try to figure out
how can I stick to what I believe
without ever needing to resort
to anger as a fuel. I can just stick to
belief. To your point about what you
want from managers, there's a graphic
image that says, "Look, all managers are
either an umbrella or a funnel."
And when the poo comes down, they're
either shielding their team with the
umbrella or they're a funnel dropping it
onto their team. And you were discussing
the funnel, the the one who's just like,
"Yeah, we'll deal with it."
And what What are they doing?
They're deciding
that if you're the engineer,
they have a choice between push back on
the boss above them, which feels scary
and dangerous,
and push back on you being upset that
you're being asked to do weekend
maintenance for the fourth weekend. And
you're an easier target.
because I have rank, I have position, I
control your performance review, I
control your salary to some degree. So,
they're making a choice, which is it's
easier for me, safer for me.
And what you have to do in that trick in
that space
is
change that balance of safety.
So, you either have to help them feel
safe pushing back on their boss
or help them feel not safe
asking for your fourth weekend.
Those are those are the only two
choices, really, is you change the
balance of safety.
Well, that first one
almost feels impossible to me. Like, if
I was if I was reporting to someone and
this manager just says yes to
everything, has no backbone,
I don't know how I can give them a
backbone, but I can definitely do the
second option.
Well, you give them a backbone exactly
by the the second option, but like this.
You say,
let's say I'm your manager. You say,
"Hey Ethan,
um
this is
there seems to be a pattern where we
keep getting asked to do weekend work.
I would love to help you push back on
that about how that's damaging our team,
distracting our team. I can give you
some of the data.
But, I also have to be clear with you
that
my family is very important to me and I
can't keep working weekends. And so,
what I don't want is for you to be in a
position where you accept work
that I'm going to have to decline and
then you'll have the problem that you
committed to it and it won't happen.
And so, I don't want to see you in that
position. How can we plan to push back
next time?
That's
that's how you line it up
in advance. And I've I've heard this
exact situation from a friend. Their
manager was a yes-man to manage their
manager.
>> Very common. And so, they were doing
committing to all these unreasonable
deadlines and you know, not protected at
all and wasn't a big deal cuz there's
turnover, but it's fine. Just hire new
people and just keep saying yes to more
and driving people as hard as you can.
The narrative that you said there, it it
felt slightly more threatening than the
the other ones cuz I I could imagine I
could imagine that that more directly
feels like
you're threatening not to do the work.
So, number one, you're right. That
wasn't as polished as some of the other
lines I've given you.
But, I think with 5 minutes I could
create a more polished version.
And one of the keys that you're getting
at here is the wrong time to start
setting this up is while the request is
in hand.
What you want to do, like if you're
getting asked to work every weekend, the
right time to have this discussion with
your boss is like Tuesday or Wednesday.
Bef- after the weekend's over and a
little time has passed
and before the next crisis arrives.
And the second piece though is it's then
how do you make clear that your
tolerance is limited? And yes, one of
the costs of that, this is important.
If you're not willing
for the manager to say, "Well, if you
don't like it, quit."
You can't say anything. [snorts]
You've got to have enough confidence in
yourself that if it does come to that,
like when I went to my manager
and I said,
"Um
I need to know how important
uh my career is to Amazon." I was also
looking for an outside job.
Um
like I had decided
I'm going to do everything I can
diplomatically to win this over, but I'm
also okay leaving.
I think that's a big difference between
this situation and all the other ones,
which is
in all the other situations, you had
leverage. The you could leave and they
will
they would feel pain. Whereas in this
case, if you're the lowly person or
engineer, maybe they don't see your
value as much. If you leave, you say,
"Okay, great. Goodbye."
>> um I mean, if you really are that
discardable, then you've
not created much value.
In other words,
absolutely
leverage is required, but good engineers
are valuable. And
teams that are total turnover factories
are not that effective. Now, if there's
a company that totally has a view of
bring them in, burn them out, move them
on,
you're probably in the wrong place.
Like, that is, you know, if you're at a
place where you can't create any sort of
value,
the right answer is you will have to get
out.
Um
And I think people get trapped believing
there isn't a better option.
There's always more jobs. And I'm not
belittling long searches or the
difficulty or all all the problems, you
know, with maybe in engineering today of
AI making it hard to get on entry level,
but
but there are jobs if you do enough
work. So, one of the things you have to
ask yourself is
this
being at the bottom of the funnel
of
bad work being rained down upon you,
how bad is that compared to say doing
the extra work
to network and find something else or
start your own thing?
Uh
don't be a victim.
You have agency.
Uh if you prefer, you know, you can look
at ownership, the book Extreme Ownership
by Jocko Willink, whatever. There's many
ways to look at it, but
in the end, you have to
be willing to take control of your life.
Um even if that does mean, by the way,
that you weather the bad manager while
you complete the training program or
find the job.
Uh what a lot of people like to do is
complain about how unhappy they are, but
not do anything else.
I get it because it seems exhausting.
Like, "Oh, I just worked all day and now
I worked all weekend. When am I going to
look for a job?"
Um one of my beliefs is to work less,
you often have to work more first.
Right? In other words, to get to the
place where you can coast or have a good
situation, you have to have to do some
ugly digging first. And this
the situation you're setting up is one
of those.
You also hit on another point that's
really important.
Create leverage.
If you create that leverage,
you're always in the winning situation.
And then, thing is, if you stick is long
enough, if your lever is long enough, it
doesn't take very much force, which is
why I'm able to be polite about it.
I can be very soft in my hints about
what I like because the lever is so
strong. People are like, "Oh,
we want to make this work right away."
And that's what you're trying to do is
have a big lever.
I guess on another topic, there's the
skill of backchanneling, which is
not in public forums, but one-on-one in
different places Yeah. driving your
message to the right people so that you
get the right aligned outcome. So,
how do you effectively backchannel?
So, I think of backchanneling in two
ways. There's good backchanneling and
manipulative backchanneling.
Manipulative backchanneling is where I'm
trying to do something that I wouldn't
be willing to say in public. So, that's
where you're really undermining or
painting the other
other proposal or the other leader
in a negative light.
Um
I don't think that's usually necessary.
And I'd like to say never necessary, but
you'll lose some cuz maybe they'll do
that.
Uh
what
positive backchanneling is
is giving people a chance to ask
questions and find out what their
concerns are where they don't have to
bring them out in public. So, maybe for
example,
I'm the CFO or I'm the financial person
and I'm really concerned about the
budget, but I don't want to just ask a
bunch of budget questions in the meeting
or I don't want to put you on the spot.
Or maybe I don't realize that you're
mostly concerned about the budget.
If we have a backchannel conversation, I
can ask, "Here's my idea. Is there
anything you don't understand? Do you
have any concerns?" And what I'm doing
there is I'm giving you a chance to
feel, remember, feelings and narrative.
I'm giving you a chance to feel
understood, to feel consulted, to feel
listened to.
Backchanneling doesn't just work
because of information exchange. You do
get data and that is good.
But, it also works because you
there's all this subconscious
I made you feel important. I made you
feel listened to. I made you feel heard.
And that emotional buy-in, particularly
if the other project leader
doesn't do that,
gives you a huge leg up because you're
building trust. You're building trust
that, "Oh, you take input. Oh, I can
work with you." And so, even if the two
proposals are equal or even if the other
one's a little better, remember, part of
my bet if I'm an in the funding
proposals
is who can I count on when the chips are
down?
Who can I count on to get this across
the line? Who can I count on if there's
a problem?
This other leader I don't know as well.
They didn't consult me. Ryan came to me
and asked me my input and and showed
understanding for my needs.
Totally I'm funding that. Because even
though the payoff's a little lower, I'm
sure Ryan's going to come through or I
can work with him.
And so
just realize
we so underestimate emotions.
As an executive making a decision on
which project to fund
I'm
wondering how it's going to make me
look. I'm wondering what happens if it
goes wrong. I'm wondering what happens
if there's conflict between you and me
later. You going to resolve it
reasonably? I have all these fears and
worries and the back channel lets me
quiet those down as well as address
factual concerns.
And so that's why it's so effective.
I I think if you were to negatively back
channel
other people would see that you are a
snake and then you would lose
some
rapport, I guess. People do negatively
back channel
and they have to be careful about how
they get caught, right? Or or don't get
caught. You know, this is what you would
call a backroom deal. You know, the
classic backroom deal is like the
kickback where
you support this and I'll make sure
you're taken care of. It's kind of like,
you know, a mafia movie or something,
right? It's the It's the
I'm coming you with a proposal that
amounts to you should do the wrong thing
because we're both going to benefit and
I just want to make sure we're on the
same page and you know that even though
I'm actually a snake, I'm not going to
bite you. We're we're snakes together.
That's the essence of that offer.
>> Oh, no. And you know, some people are up
for that. Like because
some people are selfish and ambition
runs wild and there are absolutely
people who
look at the world and say
well
I had to pay my dues and I got screwed
over when I was in the weak position.
And so now that I'm in the strong
position, it's my right to take all I
didn't get.
It's not really I'm screwing that See,
they always tell themselves a story that
makes themselves look better. It's not
really I'm screwing those people. It's
that I'm getting what I'm owed.
Like this is only fair.
And
that's another thing that's really
important is just
when you're dealing with someone who
seems to be
vicious
do at least realize that their story to
themselves is not that they're evil.
Their story to themselves is something
else and if you can
figure out their story, you have a
better chance to redirect that story.
We talked a lot about soft power and
influence and it it it sounds to me like
that's not necessarily directly
proportional to how many recursive
reports you have. Have you seen examples
where there was a person within an org
that had a disproportion amount of
influence? Yeah. Well, the first thing I
would say
>> [clears throat]
>> is
I've seen soft power
come from ideas a few times.
So
Amazon for a while built a product they
called it Cloud Drive ultimately, but it
was a storage system kind of like Box
uh or Dropbox, either one.
Um
and
that proposal came from an entry-level
new college graduate engineer.
He had an idea for it.
And he did two things to get it heard.
The first was Amazon had an invite-only
engineering conference where only a tiny
percentage of engineers went offsite to
this conference, but you could get an
invite by making a proposal.
So he fought his way into this
conference.
Then he knew Jeff Bezos came and
reviewed a idea poster session. And so
he emailed Jeff and said, "I have this
idea and I'm going to be at the poster
session. Do you think you could stop by
my poster?" Which is a very small ask of
the CEO.
Well, then he got an audience with Jeff
and he pitched his idea. And what Jeff
did was like it and email his triple
skip.
So my boss.
So there was
Jeff, then this VP, then me, then a
manager
then this new engineer.
And my VP didn't like the answer the
idea at all, but Jeff had said, "Look
into it."
And so
you know, I and the project I funded. It
got built.
So
outsized influence and I can I can tell
another story about this.
Whilst different people have different
origin stories for it to some degree
I worked with a slightly more senior
person who created the Amazon Fire TV or
helped put forward the proposal for it.
And he also was not a super senior
person
but he did a lot of the legwork and had
the knowledge and had the connections
and managed to get that created.
So
um what
works here
how you get that outsized influence,
I've seen it many times.
You have to have an idea
and again, it's that appealing
storytelling. You're telling a vision.
These guys were telling visions.
Wouldn't it be great if we had a cloud
storage system?
Wouldn't it be great if we had a
low-cost living room device where people
could watch Prime Video?
They were telling
an understandable soundbite story that
everyone agreed with.
At least on the surface because wouldn't
it be great if we had a cloud storage
system? Yeah. Wouldn't it be great if we
had you know, a living room device a
low-cost living room device? Yeah,
sounds great. Oh, well, look, here's
here's a way we could do it.
So I don't know if you have a follow-up
question on that, but
influence can come from anywhere.
It usually
begins with a good story
based in some real fact. It can't be
usually total nonsense.
And then
told with enthusiasm and told repeatedly
and specifically
told to people who have the power to do
it.
What about what are the the least
discussed reasons that people get fired
that you wouldn't see in in the
performance notes, but they are there?
So kind of the
that that second thing that's actually
getting someone fired
when there's a upfront story told in the
perf notes.
There's a lot of rules about when you
can and can't fire someone. And so
almost always the public story is some
sort of performance story because that's
the one thing that's allowed.
So
the hidden reasons are often if they're
not
evil or the person isn't
just doing wrong work, it's usually
incompatibility.
So the main reason I see people
getting let go
that isn't discussed is their style and
the leader's style are very different.
And that style can just be
one person is very detail-oriented,
one person is very high-level and this
can be on either end.
That's one type of incompatibility.
Another one can be
uh with engineers, it's often
one person wants to be very
tech-oriented and what's the best
technology and the other person wants to
be very business outcome-oriented of
look, what makes the money? I don't care
if it's a hack.
And
where the firing occurs is where that
becomes a religious debate
and the two are just sort of at each
other's throats. And remember, what
starts as a small thing often builds up
where over time these become a label.
That person is technically clueless.
That person's only about money.
And and they start labeling each other
and then it becomes personal.
And once it's personal
I've decided you're a bad person and I
see all these things that make you bad.
And you've decided I'm a bad manager.
And once you have this lens
you're a bad manager, it really doesn't
matter what I do. You'll see everything
I do is bad because so many things are
ambiguous and open to interpretation.
That's where people get fired. But of
course, it's always labeled somehow
performance.
Well, you mentioned it can be labeled
performance, but you mentioned that you
could get fired for performance, but
there's also those other HR reasons like
sexual harassment and those types of
things, right?
I've seen one of the most blatant cases
in my opinion of sexual harassment.
Uh I have to be careful even now what I
share and that will make the point.
There was an executive hired very
high-level position a chief level
position who immediately
started harassing women.
And he was so blatant that it ultimately
when we asked one of the HR
representatives on his team about had
she gotten any complaints, she started
crying because he had harassed her, too.
So this is someone with the
gall to harass
a woman in human resources.
Um
but
he disappeared. This the leader
terminated him right away as soon as
this came out.
But I people ask me, "How did such a
person get in here? Didn't we check
references?" And the thing I want people
to understand is
we didn't have legal proof of this
harassment. We had a lot of people who
said it happened to them. We believed
them, but we never took it through a
court and got a judgment that said, "Oh,
he's a harasser."
So, even though that's true, if I name
this person and say, "Don't ever hire
Fred Smith,
you know, he harasses women."
Fred can sue me cuz I have no proof of
that. I have no legal proof. I know it's
true, he knows it's true.
It
So, that's why companies don't say it.
So, when someone calls up and asks about
Fred, I refer them to HR, and HR says,
"Oh, Fred was employed here from this
date to that date."
And you know, they uh
that's how they keep getting hired.
I will say I've looked this person up on
LinkedIn since then.
And the
the fact he ever worked at Amazon isn't
even on his resume.
We caught it quick enough, he just
deleted it. No awkward questions there,
no why were you only there a month. He
just deleted it, moved on, and that's
how they survive. So, yeah, I've I've
seen
and it's hard to stop that. Was the next
place that that person worked more than
1 month? Or I guess they
>> maybe he was more careful. You know,
maybe because we caught it so quick, I
don't know.
Um I I don't believe
that what he did at our workplace was a
one-off.
I don't believe that.
Um but you know, of course I don't know
that. Last time we met, you mentioned
that
you as a manager could fire any one
engineer that you wanted. Is there ever
a case where you want to fire someone,
or let's say a manager wants to fire
someone, but their skip says, "You
can't." Because the skip sees it and
goes, "That's clearly there's an
ulterior motive here. That person's
fine." Like has that Have you ever seen
that overruling? I have. I've definitely
seen a case where a manager floats the
idea, "I'm not sure Ryan's the right
person for us." And the manager
knows your work
and says, "Why don't I move Ryan over
here?"
Right? Why don't I I think Ryan and
again, if I want to make you feel good
about it as a manager, what I would say
is I say, "You know,
I see that you're struggling with Ryan.
I've seen him do well in other
environments.
Let me move him to this other place.
He'll be out of your hair, and I think
he'll be fine there." I don't tell them
that I think you're going to be great
there cuz that's s- kind of hinting that
they're bad.
I just make it socially easy for them to
say, "Sure, move him away." That's just
as good as fired from my viewpoint.
Um
this relies on your skip, of course,
knowing or having a sense of things.
And again, sometimes it is just
incompatibility. Your style I can see
that you and your manager are cats and
dogs in a bag. It doesn't mean that you
can't get along well. It doesn't
necessarily mean the manager is bad. It
does mean they lack enough adaptability.
So, I can work on that.
But I may choose to save you in that
time.
Um
because
what gets forgotten is
people have personalities and
preferences
and not everyone can work for every
other boss. I certainly had managers
that some people at Amazon loved. And
they drove me batty.
And
I also know that for those managers,
they knew I was a high performer, but
they didn't like my way of doing it.
And
that's just
style does matter. You know, you have
music you like more than others. Some
music you're like, "Get this out of my
ears." And some you're like, "I can
listen to this all day."
There is some of that element in work. I
mean, the more that we talk about the
behind the scenes of how managers keep
orgs together and retain people of feels
like the orgs are they're like duct tape
together with a bunch of like uh you
know, well-worded phrases. Uh this
person goes here. Oh, I'm going to get
you what you want next half, and I'm
going to move people, and it's all kind
of
back of the envelope accounting in the
leader's mind. Is that an accurate
assessment? Uh you probably saw me smile
when you said that. I certainly feel
that way.
What I mean is managers start out like
you would think.
It's just like
I would compare it to an engineer with
an architecture.
When the project begins, you've got your
nice little lines and
lines and arrows and boxes on a page
of the system you envision. And when it
ships,
there is some resemblance to what you
drew,
but there's all these special cases you
didn't think about and all these things
you forgot that got like, "Well, what
service can we put that in cuz we're out
of time?"
And the the thing is shipped bears a
resemblance to the thing you designed,
but it is not this sort of pure,
beautiful ivory tower.
Well, I think the same is true of orgs,
where managers set out, of course, to
manage only by performance and to have
great managers and everyone happy and to
develop everyone's career, and then
reality hits of schedules and difficult
people and
locations and office changes and people
out on leave. And by the time it's all
done,
you're just really happy
that it's working, mostly.
And uh
you know, I I think that's um
I happen to enjoy military history.
There's a phrase from military history I
there military strategy that applies
here that says, you know, with your
battle plan, the enemy gets a vote.
Like it's all great you have a plan, but
then someone starts shooting at you.
Maybe if you heard it another way, the
boxer Mike Tyson said, "Everyone has a
plan till they get punched in the face."
Well, I think your manager has a plan
for a beautiful org right until like
deadlines and outages and whatever punch
them in the face, and then that plan
starts to become whatever gets them
through the fight. We talked about
individual firings for for engineers. I
think there's a common sentiment that
it's harder to fire a bad manager than
it is to fire a bad engineer.
When you had managers reporting to you
that let's say they were low-performing
managers, how do you manage them out?
So,
I think it is harder to fire managers.
There are three reasons. Reason number
one
is
they usually
are somewhat more experienced, so they
they don't have the obvious
bad performance.
Meaning uh
the first time I ever had to let someone
go it's because they stopped coming to
work. Pretty easy. Like, "Well,
it's Wednesday and you haven't been here
yet. I'm calling you to let you know
don't bother to come in tomorrow." Like
pretty cut and dry. Managers don't
usually make mistakes at that level. So,
they're more subtle. Their their
weaknesses are more subtle because they
got made a manager for some reason. They
were technically good, they were
politically good,
they were organizationally good. So,
they have some kind of strength that got
them there. That's reason one.
Reason two is a manager's work is hard
to measure.
Uh how do I exactly measure a manager's
work? Well, is it that they hired? Is it
that they did their performance reviews?
Is it that the feature shipped on time?
Is it bug count? The manager's job, it's
very hard to put a lot of metrics, which
means
when it comes time to fire or to
consider performance management,
we're in this he said, she said opinion
problem.
And I think the third reason it's tough
to fire managers
is
managers are part of the system. And so,
they know what it looks like.
They know like, "Oh, my boss isn't that
happy. How do I start positioning myself
to be hard to get rid of?" Like they
they have a quicker spidey sense.
If that's what they want you know, if
they want to stay, they have a quicker
sense of how do I
how do I make myself difficult to pin
down?
And
um
of course, it's still possible. Like I I
terminated
a large you know, not a huge number, but
a large number of managers.
It's just it's trickier. Yeah, it sounds
really hard to terminate a manager. How
do you do it then in in those cases? So,
my ideal way of doing it, which I wasn't
always able to do, is to talk to them
and to
surface the idea
socially
that
maybe this isn't working out. And would
they like to collaborate on finding a
better place?
So, I'm phrasing it as I notice I I have
the impression that we're struggling.
You know, I would say something like,
uh
"I don't think we've gotten off to the
best start here, and I'm wondering how
you feel about it. Would you like to
work on that? Or, you know, do you also
see that problem and you'd like my help
finding some other option?" Very
nebulous. Smart managers get the
message,
"I'm your boss. I'm not happy. I'm
offering you a door where I give you
some time to find a job or maybe a
severance package. Do you want to do
this the easy way?
Many managers will be like, yeah, I do.
Um, you know, and of course they'll
never say, of course you're right, I'm
failing here. I want a door. What they
will say if they're equally smooth is
they'll say,
I'm so sorry
that you're not satisfied. Of course,
I'm doing my utmost. That's me telling
you, remember,
I can make this hard for you, so you're
going to pay well for my exit. That's
that's the counter negotiation.
But,
ultimately, I want you to be happy
and satisfied with my work.
And if you're not, of course, I'd like
to discuss what changes we could make,
which is my way of saying I'm open. I'm
open to making, you know. So,
I've never used the word fired or
performance
because that creates something legally
called constructive termination. Where
if I've said, you know, we might have to
fire you, do you want to quit first?
That is a legal problem called
constructive termination where
I anything I do from that point is then
seen as I'd already decided to fire you
and now I'm making up reasons. So, I
very carefully avoided that.
They very carefully avoided ever saying,
acknowledging
that there's an actual problem. What
they say is, I'm sorry you feel that
way.
Right? Oh, I'm sorry you feel that way.
That's your problem. You feel weird
things.
But,
I want you to be happy. So, if you're
not, of course, I'd discuss
alternatives. And that's their way of
saying, yeah, okay, I get that it's not
working.
What are you going to give me?
So,
that's one way you quote-unquote fire.
The other way
um,
is classic performance management, in
which case you have to try and write
down clear goals and objectives. You
have to start documenting.
Um,
you have to give, you know, there's a
legal standard
that Well, there's a legal standard and
this is what HR wants, but you basically
have to document a bunch of expectations
and then document that they didn't hit
them. And then you have a performance
case.
Almost all managers will quit before
that.
What they'll do is once you start the
process, they'll be like, oh, okay, this
is going to take him 90 days. I have 90
days to find a new job.
And they go find a new job. You
mentioned that when the manager, who I
guess knows the system, is getting
managed out or this conversation
starting, they
can sometimes switch to how can I
extract more value for myself?
And I think a lot of people who are less
experienced or they don't know how the
system works too well
is when they're starting to get fired,
they don't
they feel they have no leverage. And the
fact that severance exists makes me
think that they do have some leverage,
although I don't know if I fully
understand it. What What is the leverage
that, let's say an engineer has as
they're getting fired
that
that a company would want to pay for?
Because severance
I mean, well, there's
>> It's a cost. There's the optics of it.
Like, it looks good, of course, but I'm
after this conversation, a little more
>> [laughter]
>> cynical. I feel like they're paying for
something for that report. So, that
report must have some leverage in that
conversation when they're getting Well,
there's several pieces of leverage. The
first is, this process, if you want to
go through it, is going to take a lot of
your time.
And uh, you have to document things. You
have to follow process. You have to
follow a bunch of paperwork. HR is going
to audit your paperwork. If you're a
low-level manager, you know, they're
going to write it. Um,
there are things I can do to string
things out
uh,
as a tactic. And so, the first offer I'm
making you is, hey, I'll save you all
that time. If you will give me some
money so that I have
money in my pocket
to go look for another job, I will save
you this time and frustration. That's
the first level of offer.
The second level of offer is the story
I'll tell the team.
Right? Is, look, I can either leave
talking about what a terrible experience
this was and what a monster you are. I
don't say those exact words to you, but
I I can show you how to say that. Um,
or I can leave saying, you know, this
just wasn't a fit for me and I'm so
excited to be moving on to Acme Inc.
And I can't speak highly enough about
how Ryan treated me through this whole
process. Ryan's amazing. So, which story
do you want me telling my coworkers?
And so, those are a couple of the pieces
of leverage. And again, it's this um,
what's that phrase of mine you like so
much? The plausible story or plausible
fiction?
>> polite fiction.
>> fiction. If I need to say this to you, I
say, well, you know,
uh, let's say I'm working for you.
Ryan,
so far, you've been nothing but
supportive. And if I were to move on to
a new job someday,
I
would, of course, explain how supportive
you've been.
But, if I if if we're discussing my
moving on, you know,
really, I would hope you'd want to
support my transition financially
so that I can tell that story.
And that's how I'd be like,
you know,
>> [gasps]
>> and even that wasn't maybe as smooth
as
I would do it if I had to. And by the
way, let's say you you're starting to
give me performance feedback and I need
time to be in the right headspace to
have this conversation with you, I would
just say that. I would just say,
you know, Ryan, um,
I appreciate you're starting to give me
some performance feedback.
I know we need to have this
conversation. Honestly, this moment, I
can't have it productively.
Let's have it tomorrow morning. Or can
we have it tomorrow morning?
Um, and most managers won't be like, no,
I need to tell you how rotten you are
right now. Because they're already on
edge a little bit. And then so, if
you're putting up this flag that says,
I'm about to lose my on you, but
tomorrow I'll be a good child, they'll
be like, sure, come back tomorrow.
Because they're sort of trained to.
And I've put you in a really difficult
situation.
This is important. Where if I've asked
for space and you say, no, we have to
finish this right now,
now I have a beef with HR.
He was so mean to me. I asked for space.
I asked if we could just talk tomorrow
morning and he said, no, I've got to
ridicule you right now.
It's very empathetic to HR.
And and now you're the one in the hot
seat. Why couldn't you give her until
tomorrow morning? Why couldn't you give
him until tomorrow afternoon? Like,
Because it So,
again, I hope I would rather coach
people on
how to be in great high-performing
situations where they're having
different conversations. But, you know,
you want to talk about the dark side and
that's okay.
I get that people want to know.
Don't be afraid to buy time. You do have
leverage.
And you may not get anything. Remember,
if your boss is starting to line you up
to terminate you,
you may not get anything. But, if you
don't ask, you certainly won't. If you
don't open the door and say, well,
you know,
what How could we make
an amicable deal? And here I'll give you
your last piece of your leverage.
Remember, your manager isn't sitting
across the table wanting to feel bad
about themselves.
They want to feel good about themselves.
And
if they have a chance to spend a little
bit of the company's money, which isn't
really their money,
so that they can look in the mirror and
say, well, it didn't work out with Ryan,
but I took care of him. I gave him a
cushion. They want to do that. And so,
they're saving them hassle. There's the
public story you're going to tell. And
there's they want to feel good about
themselves. Most managers don't like
They hate firing. They avoid it.
You know, as much as you might think,
meaning you, the listener, you, someone,
might think managers are just sitting
around going, who can I [laughter] who
can I pinch next? They're not. They
actually hate it.
When This is important. One reason
people don't survive firings is by the
time the manager actually decides, ah, I
just don't I've I've tried to coach
them. You may not feel this way, but in
their mind, they're like, I've tried to
coach them. I've tried to pair them with
people. I've tried to give them all
these chances.
And they're still not getting it. I
don't have any choice but to fire them.
Once they've gotten to where they're
going to act, they've told themselves
they're out of options, which is why
people getting back off the brink is
very unlikely.
You know, interestingly, right before I
came here to talk to you today, I had
lunch and I met a new executive. He owns
a company that does half a billion
dollars of business a year. So, it's a
big company.
He's built it over his whole life. And
he was telling me
how he's going to have to hold someone
in his organization who's a who isn't
performing. He's kept on his staff for 2
years. He's finally at the point where
he's going to have to hold them
accountable.
And what I'm thinking is he's put off
that hard message. When he finally gets
to where he's going to give it, he's so
decided that they don't meet the bar,
they can't get out of that.
And it's not because he's evil, it's
just people delay. And so
I coach people, people come to me all
the time because I'm online. They say,
"Ethan, I've just been put on a
performance improvement plan.
Can you help me survive it? Can you help
me recover?" And I tell them
honestly, no. You're most likely going
to be fired and there's nothing I can do
for you.
But here's why. It's by the time someone
gets around to giving you a form of
formal performance plan,
they've tried everything else they could
think of.
And at this point, they just want you
gone as quietly as possible.
And it happens again all the time.
People write me back and they're like,
"You don't understand. I'm going to
Three months later, I get an email from
them that says, "You were right. I was
fired."
Of course there are exceptions to this,
but it's so common that I see this
pattern of how can I survive this? I'm
going to I'm a hard worker. I'm a good
person. I'm going to show them.
Three months later, you were right. I
got fired.
Even if people had the awareness cuz I
guess they're going to listen to this
conversation,
I think they still lack that a lot of
people lack that skill of
creating the polite fiction.
You know, how do you And I I we talked
about it. We don't need to go deeper in
it, but I I do think that even if I
someone came to me and they said, "I'm
in this situation."
And I said, "Here's here's your
leverage.
Good luck." I think they would have
trouble delivering that message in a an
effective way of saying For instance,
especially the team health one cuz the
team health one is more of a threat. The
saving time one is, "Hey, I can do
something good for you. I'll leave
quietly. Just help me get some
severance."
The team health one is, "I can make this
hard for you
unless you get me severance." I think
delivering that kind of message as
you're leaving, especially when they
have such a negative bias on you
already,
that's going to take some incredible
people skills.
>> Yeah, um like yes, you're right. Okay,
this is part of the message which is
engineers in particular want to believe
this is in fact maybe the most important
message even if it's not the most
exciting which is
as an engineer, you want to believe it's
your technical expertise that controls
the fate of your career.
And it's not only that, it's your people
skills.
It's well known,
right? Sa has talked about this. Other
leaders have talked about IQ without EQ,
without emotional intelligence is a
waste of IQ.
And so
having strong
interpersonal skills
is critical. You know, it's funny.
There's a famous book you I'm sure you
know it uh by Cal Newport called So Good
They Can't Ignore You.
And what I find ironic about this is
it's all this stuff about how to be such
a good worker you can't be ignored.
Except this is a guy who has the social
skills to both teach at Princeton and
write books.
He's not without the human skills to
present his incredible technical
accomplishments
delicately and well.
So
uh
I think it's a huge area of learning.
Now, to exemplify this, how would I if I
on the spot or here, you know, live had
to construct a better way to say that?
I would say something
gentler like
um
boy,
this is such a hard message and
I have so many friends on this team.
I just I don't want them to think badly
of me. I don't want them to think this
is an unfair environment. Can you work
with me so that this is a graceful exit?
And
That's good. That works. You know, I I
don't feel like starting it at all.
And and you know, later if I need you, I
say, "Well, for you to feel good,
Yeah, [laughter] yeah, I mean, of
course, you know, like I I rub if it
you know, for you to feel good, I need
enough security to get to my next thing.
And I know you want that. I I know that
you don't want anyone to suffer and I
tie into you
>> Right, right, right. It's the other
thing. Um
but it is possible and that is why I I
said this is how you get the time to go
figure out how you're going to deliver
these messages.
Something people overrate or I guess
underrate
is recognizing that a lot of hard
messages
you don't have to deliver cold. I
mentioned this before, but you you can
buy the time or make the time
to pre-plan.
Maybe not every word. It isn't
memorizing a speech. It's more
memorizing a few phrases
and and how you're going to
you know, say what you need to in a
polite way.
I want to pivot to promos and talking
about promotions cuz I know there's a
lot of stuff going on behind the scenes
on alignment between managers and upper
leadership on who's going to get
promoted. You mentioned the queue
earlier.
Um and I think a lot of people they get
they get stuck at this staff engineer
which is equivalent to the front line
manager level of how to get the promo to
go further into those higher levels.
Do you have any advice on how to break
out of that that common level that
people get stuck at?
Yeah, I mean, this is this is my bread
and butter, what I teach every day and
kind of if I have a signature expertise,
it's how to move up further.
What generally gets people stuck is
they're
they're not
learning the new skill of the next
level. Instead, they're doing the
current skill harder and harder.
And so
what gets you promoted early in life is
hard effective work. It is hard work. It
is delivery. It is shipping a lot or
building a lot. But as you get further,
you need different skills. You need to
be able to delegate. You need to be able
to communicate. You also need to be able
to let go of your hard skills because if
you're trying to micromanage everyone
and tell them write it this way, write
it that way, build it this way, you're
driving your engineers nuts and they
you're going to drive away your good
people.
And so
the way to get to the next level is to
figure out
what do I need to let go of, step away
from, and what new thing do I need to
master? And uh there's a classic book on
this. It's by a guy named Marshall
Goldsmith. It's What Got You Here Won't
Get You There. It literally shows a
ladder with a gap in it. Like what got
you this far isn't going to get you up
there.
Um
that's kind of the classic book, but if
you
need specific advice to your role, it's
absolutely talking to people a level or
two above who've been through this and
asking them,
"What did you have to let go of?
What did you have to learn? How do I do
that? What do I need to let go of? What
do you see holding me back?"
I'm a huge
proponent of getting advice. Getting
advice is even better than getting
feedback. If I ask for feedback, I'm
basically asking you to do something
that you may
struggle to do which is criticize me. If
I ask you for advice, everyone has
advice to share. And they'll give you
the same information, but in a more
positive way.
So to break through
to that next level,
it's identify what's different about
that level and get good at that
as opposed to just work harder. I see so
many people
working brutally hard, but
ineffectively. When it comes to the most
senior promotions, I think there's this
idea of readiness which I feel like is
what you just talked about which is
developing the skills and being in the
position where your manager would say,
"Yes, this person fills out the tem But
then there's also the case of limited
number of spots and kind of positioning
yourself so that you are put in one of
those spots.
And so imagine there's a case where I'm
a senior leader and I'm maybe I'm going
for the director position. I mean, I'm
going the
the principal engineer position and
there's two of us both going for the
same time, but we both report to you.
How would I position myself so that I
get the promotion first?
Absolutely. Let's assume you're both
equally qualified for a moment. So
you're not going to win on skill. It's
there in
relationship and within relationship,
trust.
So trust
trust is about do I have to look over my
shoulder and wonder, are you doing
things not the way I would do them
exactly, but in a way that won't make me
look bad, that will, if you prefer, make
us both successful. Do I trust what
you're doing? Or do I cuz as a senior
leader, I don't have any time to
micromanage you. I'm so busy myself. I
need to be able to give you something
and assume it will get handled.
And trust, I often tell people,
interestingly,
trust is earned more in bad times than
good times.
My favorite analogy for this, which is a
little bit violent, is
when two people have been in a war
together and I had to put my life on the
line for you or you for me, we now have
a lot of trust because
if I trusted you,
like if you came through when the
bullets were flying, I know you'll come
through the rest of the time.
Well, what's the closest thing at at
work? This is usually a crisis, a big
outage, a big embarrassment, a lost
account. If you jump on that and somehow
fix it or show all the effort and it
hurts you or it costs you, you cancel a
vacation, not that I'm recommending
doing that a lot, but if you make a
decision that shows that you're
dedicated, I will remember when the
chips were down, when we lost the Acme
account,
Ryan came through. He flew back from
Hawaii early and made it. And that's
trust. Second thing is relationship.
Relationship in this case, I'm honestly
thinking of do I like you? And the point
is,
if I have two relatively equally
qualified people and I'm going to
suddenly spend more time working with
one than the other,
why would I not choose the person I
enjoy?
And
again, I know some engineers are just if
they were dead, they'd be spinning in
their graves. They hate that idea.
Look,
one person's a little bit more difficult
to work with
or even just a little bit less fun, and
the other one's more fun.
I have to spend eight hours a day with
this person or six cuz we're not in
every meeting the same.
I'm going to be drawn towards the person
that's fun.
And I know that seems unfair
uh and it doesn't mean you have to kiss
up to everyone. It does though mean it's
a good idea to be friendly and happy,
right? Like be be pleasant. Be be
be that helpful, smiling person because
I'd rather spend time with you. Um I
heard it expressed this way by Amazon
leadership, by Bezos, I think,
which is
when you come into the room,
do you suck all the oxygen out of it?
Like it you bring the room down where
the room's like
If you're that person, you're not going
far.
You're not going any further. Whereas if
when you come in, they're like
All right, like oh, Ryan's here. This
just got better.
They kind of want you in that room. And
you know, it's it's a So if you want a
simple rubric, do people want you in the
room?
If they kind of don't, you're in
trouble. And if they kind of do, you're
doing great.
I I do agree. I think a lot of engineers
are going to this is going to piss them
off, but
>> That's okay. See, It's true. what I
would say to the engineers I piss off is
I am trying to help you. I'm not
actually here because you'll like me.
I'm here to get you where you want to go
and that requires you you asked me,
could I be transparent?
Part of the transparency is sometimes
transparency is telling you things that
I know you're not going to like, but
that are holding you back and you're
letting the fact you don't like it let
you get your back up and be like, I'm
never going to do that. Well, okay, but
then you're never going to move up. And
I'm not here to apologize for the way
the world works. The way the world works
sucks, but it does work that way.
And I want people to know that. When I
think of the most senior level
promotions,
>> Mhm. baked into the promotion packets is
this idea that you need champions or
sometimes known as allies, which is
people at that level or higher that say
that person is doing work that fits
my my perception of that level. So
because of that, I've noticed there's
this artificial mechanism. Like let's
say I'm a
uh let's use management as an example.
Let's say I'm a senior manager, I want
to become a director.
All of a sudden, if I want to get
promoted, I need to make sure that that
VP over there knows my work and will
vouch for me in the promo committee and
that other VP over there. And there
there are cases where naturally I might
need to be visible in front of those
people, but there are also a lot of
cases where it's just I I need to fill
out the promo packet in the way um that
that we need so that the promo will go
through.
How would you go about that? Let's say
you are a senior a very senior engineer
or a very senior manager in tech and
you're trying to get those allies, but
there's no
at least as far as you can see, there's
no natural collaboration with those
people. How do you get them as a as a
champion on your promo packet? So I'm
going to tell you my favorite way and
then I'll give you other ways. My
favorite way is you have your boss on
your side. You've got that team with
your manager where your manager wants to
get you promoted.
And what I did in those cases is I would
email my peers or my skips and I would
say, you know, Ryan's going to be up for
promotion in 6 months. And because your
group is adjacent to ours, I'm going to
need to ask you for feedback. So I'm
letting you know that you've got 6
months to watch Ryan
because I'm going to be coming to you.
And
number one,
me asking doesn't feel self-serving cuz
I'm talking about you. And number two,
6 months later when that VP
I'm sure wants to say, well, I only saw
Ryan twice. I'm not sure if I can write
anything.
I have they know that I'm going to say
like, hey, I told you. Like I put you on
notice. Now, sometimes they'll just say,
I'm sorry, it didn't come together. I
don't know I can't provide feedback. But
that's
that's the best way. And I did that when
it when I got good at getting team
This is important as a manager. I got
good at getting my people promoted.
And that allowed me to attract more
talent because for example, I had a guy
who didn't get promoted and I said,
look, you know I'm good at this.
I I will get this done in 6 months, but
you've got to give me till the next
cycle, but you know I come through. So
you have to trust.
And he later told me, he's like, yeah,
that sucks, but I I decided I'd give you
6 months and we got it done.
So
that's the best way. Now, let's assume
your manager's not that on board or they
lack that skill or you can't sell them
on it. By the way, if you have good
relationship, I tell them like, would
you consider putting them on notice that
you're going to need feedback?
If you can't,
the next best thing is for you to go
talk to them
and say, hey, I'm up for promotion.
I'm pretty sure my manager's going to
ask you for feedback. You're a logical
feedback provider.
What can we do over the next 6 months so
that you're in a natural position to
give me you know, to give feedback? Or
you know, how could I keep you informed
of my work? What would
And
one of the keys here is if you need, you
know, whatever four champions, you're
going to have to ask six people or
seven.
Uh because one of them's going to leave
the company and one's going to get
reorged and one's going to say no. So
you have to like over subscribe. It's
like, you know, over capacity just like
anything else you design.
Um
and it is awkward. Uh
you know, to go to a like a another
group skip. But the thing is, you can
frame it to them as, hey, you know this
is our process.
Like you know, I'm sure you get requests
all the time for feedback and you
probably get a lot of late last minute
requests.
I'm trying to do it right and talk to
you 6 months in advance. And so what
you're saying there behind the lines is
see, I'm already good. I'm like not
causing you to get hit with no notice.
I'm here
you know, setting this up in advance,
making it easy for you. Well, my
immediate thought if I was that VP and
someone came to me with that
self-serving request, I wouldn't
necessarily think that's bad or
anything. I think okay, that's the
process. But my immediate thought is
this is not a high priority for me cuz
I'm I'm a VP. I got I got a billion
things on my plate and this random
person from another org is coming to me
uh to serve themselves, which not not
necessarily something I care about, but
just shows that it's low on my
priorities. How do you get them to
prioritize that? Well, remember, there
is some truth it's low on their priority
list, but they have people they need to
get promoted where they need other VPs.
See, you have a VP, too.
And
that VP
this the VP you went to knows
that they're going to need your VP's
help with some promos. And so
the leverage you have without ever
bringing it up to them is
they do know it's a system and it's kind
of part of their job. So is it a high
priority for them? No.
Um the only way you can make it a high
priority
is if you're able
to explain to them
uh
some relevance of your work. You're
going to have to give them a so a what's
called with them, what's in it for me.
You're going to have to find some way to
connect what you're doing to something
they care about at least a little bit.
How are you going to make their life
easier, faster,
less stressful?
When these systems work as designed,
those VPs do work with your area
somewhat.
And so
they should have
you
you shouldn't be asking someone who like
has no relation to your work whatsoever
ever.
It's just they don't really need your
level of detail,
but you you can
try to find some way to give them a
little bit of nugget.
Uh I do think these systems work mostly
though because
vice presidents do know that this is how
the system works and that they kind of
need to do it. And
if vice presidents are good at nothing
else, they're usually good at
understanding
this is the grease that keeps the thing
flowing. And by the way, I can write
some mild approving verbage of you
very easily.
It may look, maybe because it was like I
cut and pasted and replaced John with
Ryan,
but, you know, and replace, you know,
whatever the ops org with the the, you
know, the customer org.
But, I've written a million of these and
I can do it pretty quickly. I think a
lot of those those champion the champion
support
is a little bit contrived and it's hard
for me without my manager's support to
get uh a
You said, "What's in it for me?" Like a
a legitimate case of what's in it for
that VP cuz they're so far, they're so
high up. I mean, I know some people who
they're in this spot, they're very
senior IC. Their manager is supportive,
but they lack maybe that proactivity
that that you have. And obviously the
the engineer has the proactivity for
their own case. So,
they they debate, you know, should they
go directly to that person? If so, how?
Cuz it doesn't they don't have a great
case.
Yeah, and I think I think that coaching
your own manager works pretty well in
this sense. Your manager often knows
what they need to do or at least is open
to it and it just hasn't made their
priority list because
you obviously care more about your
career than your manager does usually,
right? Cuz it's like that's just human
nature. And so, the manager means well
and wants to help, but isn't
isn't getting around to it. And so, if
you just poke them a little bit.
The other thing that is a middle ground
is you can ask your manager, "Would you
send a note to that VP? Like I know I
need to go
get them to support me, but I don't
really know them. Can you send them a
quick intro that says, 'Hey, I have a
guy who's coming up for promotion. Uh he
wants to come talk to you, you know,
would you take a 15-minute meeting
uh because we're going to need your
feedback.'"
It still gives you you still are doing
most of the work, they're just sending
an email, but it that's a middle ground.
Um you've opened a topic though I really
want to point out to all the engineers.
You asked me if I'd ever seen a case
where a skip level
uh saved an engineer from being fired.
And I said, "Yeah, I've seen people
moved around."
What I never really seen is an engineer
or any other anybody else get promoted
over their manager's objection. You have
to have your manager's support because
I can't if I'm the big boss, I can't
promote you if the manager doesn't agree
because I'm just creating a mess. I'm
telling the manager they're wrong and
now I'm telling them that they have to
work with you more senior, you know,
even though they didn't agree. I'm just
creating a complete mess. So, if the
manager isn't supportive,
I think engineers envision like I'm
going to do such incredible work and I'm
so technically astute that I will be
recognized even though this manager is a
bozo.
It's not going to happen. It just it
can't. And so, you either have to get
your manager on board or get out from
under them and find somebody who is on
board.
Now,
a plug for people like me. Go find the
managers who
I made a profession of getting people
moved up, not undeservedly, but fast.
And hell, that became a huge selling
point, right? Go to Ethan's org, he'll
make deals and get you promoted.
That was my recruiting tool. Come work
for me and I'll make it happen.
Because it was known that I would back
people and get the job done,
I could attract talent.
And I could keep talent. I had one guy
in my my
biggest star employee
uh began as a mid-level engineer, what
Amazon calls a level five.
He went to a senior engineer, he moved
to manager, from manager at an equal
sort of lateral promo, he went to senior
manager, then to director.
And by that point he caught up to me. I
was a director, too. So, we were out of
space and he went to found his own
company. Now, he was a top performer,
but three promotions in eight years. We
worked together eight years.
You know, we're still close friends, of
course, but he powered my career and I
powered his.
But, that example also brought other
people.
Like, "Oh, look at look at what happens
in this org."
We've been talking about politics for
almost 3 hours now and I can feel it
many at many points people listening are
probably thinking,
"I hate every single moment of this. I I
hate this." I just some people are
probably listening because they they
feel like they have to, but they wish
they didn't have to know how the system
works.
And I know it's inevitable a little bit
that, you know, you can't avoid politics
completely. But, let's just say for
someone who really just despises
politics for all it is, what could you
do to avoid politics if you were working
at a company?
I think number one, it's about choosing
your leader. So, if you can find a
leader who shares your disdain of
politics, hopefully, that maybe comes
from a similar tech background and wants
to reward they believe as much as you do
it should be all about the work,
find that leader. That's one thing you
can do. The second thing is go work on
the hardest area you can get into where
expertise is really going to matter and
you can stand out the most. In other
words, if you're doing
good solid engineering work, but that
lots of people can do, it's harder to
stand out. I remember Andy Jassy, he was
CEO of AWS at this time, but in the past
he had been
uh I'm sorry, before he was CEO of all
of the Amazon.
And he was talking about principal
engineers and he said, "Principal
engineers are normally expected to like
advise others and mentor and do
architecture.
But, these guys, these few guys working
on AWS, we just need them solving the
hardest problems and so, I absolve them
of all of that other stuff."
Well, for those engineers who just
wanted to be
"I don't want to review architecture. I
don't want to give feedback. I don't
want to promote I s-
he was the perfect boss because he felt
they're they were working on such hard
problems he couldn't spare them
to invest in the rest of the org and he
didn't care. So, you're looking for that
situation where your work is so
essential.
Uh because absolutely, look, you've
asked about difficult people and I've
given you all these rules about it's
great that your boss it's important your
boss like you.
If you have a skill that no one else
has,
and that skill is valuable, you will get
exceptions. I remember
Andy
again, when he ran AWS, I remember him
talking about
a high-level employee
who
a couple people criticized him and said,
"That guy's not working that hard.
You know, he's not really working at an
Amazon level."
And Andy said, "Yeah, I think you're
right,
but
he's in a role where we need him and I
think he knows we need him. And so,
we're just going to have to live with
it." Like, he does the one thing we
really need. And you could kind of tell
Andy was like Andy's
one of the hardest managers I ever
worked for. Just very demanding.
But, in this case he's like, "Yeah, he's
got the leverage.
It is what it is." You know, and he was
very like
"Good on him." was kind of his, you
know, like, "Yeah, he's kind of got us.
We're just going to have to live with
it."
Uh that's what you have to do if you
don't want politics is you've got to be
you've got to have that essential skill.
Um again, you have to have some kind of
leverage. So,
you have to literally live up to Cal
Newport in So Good They Can't Ignore
You.
Earlier in our conversation you talked
about how when everything's growing it's
positive
sum, when everything is kind of stagnant
in an organization it's a little more
zero sum where people are battling. So,
I can also imagine a growing company is
much less likely or will have less
politics. I think some amount is um I
like to give people an extreme to think
about. Uh and my extreme I often point
out is the post office.
Like, what's going on good at the post
office? And the only kind of roles are
carry the mail or be the postmaster and
there's one postmaster.
And that until that person leaves or
dies,
you don't get that job. And so,
it just feels like growth changes so
much of that because it's not 25 people
wanting one promotion, it's
you know,
lots of opportunity.
And
I point out
during the 15 years I was at Amazon,
the staff size of the company, I joined
it was 14,000 people, I left it was 1.4
million.
So, it grew a hundredfold, which is
insane.
As a result, I was able my first team
there was six people and nine years
later I had 800.
That kind of growth
opens up doors that in a more normal
company that's maybe growing 5% a year
or 10% a year, it's just never going to
happen. So, I strongly believe find high
growth. Last question is if you could go
back to yourself at the beginning of
your career and give yourself some
advice specifically focused on this, I
guess, navigating corporate politics, is
there something that that stands out to
you that you'd say?
Yeah, I God, I wish I could go back to
early me
and share the idea that uh
it's not just being right.
It's It's
not just being right. It's not just
being technically astute. There's all
this other stuff going on and wake up to
it. I think I was blind or deprioritized
it and thought, "Well, that's
that's management stuff." And even as an
individual contributor, understanding
well, management stuff does control the
world. I wish I had been more aware. So,
I guess the advice to get it down to a
single sentence is
take it seriously
that your relationships are what
actually control your progress.
Awesome. All right. Well, thank you so
much for your time, Ethan. I really
appreciate it. Thank you so much for the
chance to do this a second time. It's
been so much fun and the time has flown
by. Also, and do you want to plug um
your your stuff [laughter] real quick?
Well, I think if you've gotten something
from this discussion and you want to
know how to navigate your career, that's
what I do all the time. I teach classes
on it. I have a newsletter on it. So, if
you want help, my goal is to help people
succeed rather than bang their head
against walls. If I've done some of that
in this podcast, I can do more of it
with more time.
All right. 3 and 1/2 hours in the chair.
Thank you. Thank you.
>> [laughter]
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So, I'd love
to show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market. So,
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilya Grigoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also,
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhangers in
the intros. So, your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show and I'll see you in the next
episode.